<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The King's evidence justifi'd, or, Doctor Oates's vindication of himself and the reality of the plot against a traiterous libel called The compendium contrived by the Jesuits, to the dishonour of the King and kingdom.</title>
            <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O46</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22091</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11929783</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11929783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70752)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 770:8 or 1001:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The King's evidence justifi'd, or, Doctor Oates's vindication of himself and the reality of the plot against a traiterous libel called The compendium contrived by the Jesuits, to the dishonour of the King and kingdom.</title>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 53 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Edwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 1001:21 as Wing D189 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.) and at reel 770:8 as Wing O46.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Huntington Library and the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Castlemaine, Roger Palmer, --  Earl of, 1634-1705. --  Compendium.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  England.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51086:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51086:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE KING's Evidence JUSTIFI'D: OR Doctor OATES's VINDICATION of Himſelf, And the Reality of the PLOT, AGAINST <hi>A Traiterous Libel,</hi> CALLED The Compendium; Contrived by the JESUITS, To the Diſhonour of the <hi>King and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>Theog. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. v. 613.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Quanto perditior quiſque eſt, tanto acrius urget. <bibl>
                  <hi>Horace. Sat 1, 2, 15</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Edwin,</hi> at the Three Roſes in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:51086:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51086:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO ALL Our Worthy Patriots, And all other <hi>Impartial Readers,</hi> OF WHAT Rank or Condition ſoever.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere it not, but that the Inveterate Rage, and partial Obſtinacy of thoſe that labour to defend the ſilly Poppetry of the Roman Catholick Religion, if I may ſo terme it, has been ſo apparent for many Ages, It might be matter of Amazement, how it could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly happen, that after ſo many Legal Tryals, and thoſe alſo publiſh'd by the Chief Judges of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſhew the World how guilty the Papiſts have been, any Subject of the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould dare to be ſo hardy, as to Print his muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Reflections upon the Concernments of his Soveraign and arrogant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joſtle the Votes of the Parliament of the Nation in both their Houſes. But there are great men in the ſame Danger; and Policy with Reward, goes beyond Strength. The moſt Unfortunate Mr. <hi>Reading</hi> took the wrong courſe, to tamper clandeſtinly with a ſingle Witneſs. Here's one aimes at the full breaſt of Truth: He ſhall have all the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds a Year</hi> to himſelf, and the Land in <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire</hi> to boot. For aſſuredly, this <hi>Compendium</hi> is but an Engine contriv'd by Men of leaſure, to batter down thoſe Teſtimonies which they themſelves are conſcious to be moſt fairly levell'd at their Crimes. This is call'd <hi>Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> in the <hi>Interim,</hi> and agrees with Policy and Self-preſervation. For truly, if the Gentleman has given himſelf all this trouble out of pure Zeal, it argues him to have little Religion; ſince no bad Subject can be a good Chriſtian. He might have allow'd his Prince ſo much Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, as to be able to judge of Crimes committed againſt himſelf; or otherwiſe have been more reſpectful to his Royal Dignity, then in the Metropolis of his Dominions, publickly to tax him with ſhedding Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51086:3"/>Blood? and from thence to inſinuate an arrogant kind of Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Soveraign, to be more Cautious and Wary for the future. Which being the abſolute and only Conſtruction to be made of all his Toyle, I would fain ask the Rational world this Queſtion, what would have been the unhappy Fate of a <hi>Compendium</hi> of this nature, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Proteſtants in their own juſtification, under the juriſdiction of the <hi>Inquiſition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſetting aſide all his Marginal Induſtery, which has coſt him the Expence of a <hi>Rhodomando;</hi> and his gaudy mixtures of Roman and Italick: he muſt not think to vapour here in <hi>England</hi> with his falſe Aſſertions, that the Diſpute is ſtill on foot, unleſs it be among Fools and thoſe of his own Party; or that the Champions for his Friends ſtill keep their Ground, unleſs it be within the Liſts of <hi>Rome</hi> or St. <hi>Omers.</hi> And let him wonder till Dooms-day, the <hi>Epitomiſer</hi> will find the want of Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion very erroniouſly thrown upon the <hi>Good People.</hi> For, when his beloved Friends put themſelves upon their Country; their Country then, who were the people, as able, as the <hi>Epitomizers Worſhip,</hi> to judge of an Evidence, were perſons of that Integrity, that they would not have found them Guilty, unleſs they had <hi>well Examin'd</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at their Tryals: And there was then as much ſpoken at the Bar, as was afterwards made publick to the World. But he thinks 'tis time to ſtop the Currant of the Peoples Examination of things, which has oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd the truſſing up of ſo many of his dear Brethren in ſeveral parts of the Nation, beſides what are ſtill in deſerved Captivity; ſome of which are diſcover'd to be as Infamous for their Debauchery, as their open Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity againſt the Laws of the Land. I would fain know of the Mr. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomiſer,</hi> whether he thought the King and Council, were not in the ſame fault with the ignorant people, when His Majeſty was pleaſed to Iſſue forth his Warrants to the Judges of Aſſize for the Execution of thoſe that lay Condemn'd in the Country Jayles?</p>
            <p>The laſt Paragraph of his <hi>Dedication</hi> looks like one of <hi>Poor Robins Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements,</hi> made only for the advantage of the <hi>Printer,</hi> who, as his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence foreſaw, would be no great gainer by this exact <hi>Compendium</hi> of his; and therefore he ſtrains hard, to give it the beſt Encomium he can at the beginning, for pithineſs and briefneſs, to launch it into the world; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadging it to be five times better then the late <hi>Hiſtory of the Plot,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis five times ſhorter. Nay, he is ſo conceited of his Exactneſs, that he expecteth that all the Executed Criminals, ſhould Riſe again and admire it. Elſe what he means by the <hi>Perſons concern'd,</hi> will be a great doubt among the Criticks. For the <hi>Kings Evidence</hi> who are Alive, are no way Concern'd, but only to let him know, that ſuch puny Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, muſt not paſs uncorrected. And ſo to the matter it ſelf.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning Mr.</hi> Coleman.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Epitomizer</hi> begins his Laborious Abbreviation with that of <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Tryal; where he comes with the Sheirs of his Conſideration, and falls a pruning, as if he were at work by the Great. Were it poſſible for his Libel to ſucceed, you ſhould ſee he would fall a ſnipping again, till he had brought it within the compaſs of a Nut-ſhell, to be worn about
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51086:3"/>the Ivory Necks of Ladies, in honour of the within-mention'd Martyrs. Now, for the better and more plauſible carrying on his Deſign, he Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges and Defies any man to ſhew him where he has leſſen'd the force either of the Charge or Anſwer. But ſuch is the Nature of theſe be-je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited Bygots, that they can as well leave their Leaſing, as the Catt, turn'd to a Woman in the Fable, could leave her Mouſing. What is it to the World, whether he cite true, if he do not quote all? Or, if he leave out the moſt Material Points that make againſt him? It may be he ſtates the Charge right, but he leaves out the Principal Anſwer made to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Now whither this be not True, let the firſt Proof of the <hi>Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizer</hi>'s Honeſty determine.</p>
               <p>He Sums up Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Evidence in theſe Words: That in <hi>November</hi> 1678. <hi>Coleman</hi> did write Letters by him to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> in which he called the King <hi>Tyrant;</hi> and ſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 17, &amp; 18.</note> That the Match with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> would prove the <hi>Tyrants</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> Ruine. That a Letter under <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> hand, was alſo then incloſed to <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> thanking him for the <hi>Ten Thouſand Pound</hi> which he promiſed ſhould be employ'd to no other Uſe but to cut off the King. That this Letter was written by the <hi>Provincial Strange</hi>'s direction, becauſe he<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> had hurt his hand, and <hi>Mico</hi> his Secretary was ill. That the Anſwer was carried to <hi>Paris,</hi> where <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> ask'd him how the Dutcheſs's Secretary did? That the Anſwer written by <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> was ſent to <hi>Coleman,</hi> after it had been firſt perus'd by the Society, in Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s preſence; who, by a Patent from them, was of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and had Power to open Letters. That in <hi>April,</hi> 78. there was a Conſult of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> at the <hi>white-Horſe-Tavern</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> to ſend <hi>Cary</hi> to <hi>Rome.</hi> That afterwards they Adjourned into ſeveral Clubs,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> and pitch'd upon <hi>Grove</hi> and <hi>Pickering,</hi> to Kill the KING; the one being to have 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and the other 30000 Maſſes. That this Reſolve was Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to <hi>Coleman</hi> in Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s preſence, at <hi>Wild-Houſe.</hi> That the Perſons that came over with <hi>Oates,</hi> were F. <hi>Warren,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Preston,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Francis Williams,</hi> Sir <hi>J. Warner,</hi> &amp;c. That in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> there was a Conſult of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Benedictines,</hi> at the <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Here the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> makes a ſlight Cavil, pretending that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in all the reſt of the <hi>Tryals,</hi> fix'd this Conſult upon the <hi>21ſt.</hi> of <hi>August;</hi> as if the <hi>Twenty-first</hi> Day, were not part of the ſame Month.</p>
               <p>Then he goes on with his Summary: That at the ſame time, Letters came from <hi>Talbot,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> that Four <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were to Kill the Duke of <hi>Ormond;</hi> and if they miſt, Dr. <hi>Fogarthy</hi> was to Poyſon him: To which purpoſe, <hi>Coleman</hi> was very forward to have him Diſpatched away. That 40000. Black Bills were provided to be ſent into <hi>Ireland.</hi> That <hi>Coleman</hi> told <hi>Fenwick,</hi> He had found a way to ſend 200000 <hi>l.</hi> thither,<note place="margin">Pag <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> to carry on the Rebellion. That the Four other <hi>Ruffians,</hi> procured by Dr. <hi>Fogarthy,</hi> were ſent in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to Kill the KING at <hi>Windſor.</hi> That the next Day after, <hi>Harcourt</hi> made a Proviſion of 80 <hi>l.</hi> to be ſent them; and that <hi>Coleman</hi> gave the Meſſenger a Guinney, to expedite his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. That <hi>Coleman</hi> ſaw the Inſtructions, which <hi>Aſhby</hi> brought from <hi>White,</hi> then at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> about 10000 <hi>l.</hi> for Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> to Poyſon the KING, in caſe the Aſſaſſinates fail'd. That <hi>Coleman</hi> thought it too little;<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> and took a Copy of the Inſtructions, to ſend them to the ſeveral Conſpirators in the Country, to encourage their Contributions. That he acknowledg'd the Receipt of his Patent for Secretary of State; which was ſeal'd with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Seal, and ſign'd by their <hi>General.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51086:4"/>This was the Subſtance of the Charge, as the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> has ſumm'd it up: And one would think, it was as home and cloſe an Accuſation, as could be laid upon any Man's Shoulders. Neither were the Proofs of it leſs Poſitive: The Time, ſo far as the Law requir'd; the Places, and ſeveral other Circumſtances abſolutely ſworn to: The Senſe of the Words, if not the Words themſelves, ſeverely affirm'd: And the whole Relation was rational, plain, and probable. For, what Impoſſibility was there, but that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> might act, do, hear, and ſee thoſe Things, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Depoſitions? But they that were the Maſters of Evaſion, were not ſo eaſily put out of Countenance. Now therefore, ſee how the <hi>Salmon</hi> Flounces in the Net: For the Priſoner's Defence is thus Ironical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and partially abbreviated; plainly ſhewing, which way the Byaſs of the <hi>Epitomizer</hi>'s Affection runs. That now forſooth, <hi>Oates</hi> pretends to be extreamly well-acquainted with him, and a World of Intimacy, even at Conſults and Meetings about the KING'S Death; whereas before the Council, he told His Majeſty, <hi>He did not know him.</hi> That <hi>Oates</hi> was then ſo far from laying any Poſitive Treaſon to his Charge, (for as for the Payment of the 5000 <hi>l.</hi> to Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> 'twas a Hear-ſay, as not ſeen by <hi>Oates</hi>) that the Board, after they had heard his Defence, did inſtead of ſending him to <hi>Newgate,</hi> Commit him only to a Meſſenger, till his Papers were Examin'd. And whereas <hi>Oates</hi> Accus'd him at that time, of ordering (about the <hi>21ſt.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi>) 80 <hi>l.</hi> for the <hi>Windſor-Ruffians,</hi> and giving the Meſſenger a Guinney; He was then in <hi>Warkwick-ſhire,</hi> having left <hi>London</hi> on the <hi>15th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> never returning till the <hi>31ſt.</hi> late at Night.</p>
               <p>This is the ſum of <hi>Coleman's</hi> Pigmy Defence, againſt an Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo vaſt and Giant-like. So that the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> finding the Defence to be ſo weak and invalid, Epitomizes Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Reply with a Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. Only upon the firſt Part, where the Priſoner wonders, how <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> ſhould pretend ſo much Intimacy with him, and yet tell the King he never knew him, there the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> is like the Doctor, that went to curtal <hi>Zabarel,</hi> but made the Book bigger then it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oates,</hi> ſaith He, reply'd, That he ſaid at the Council, he could not Swear he had ſeen him before, <hi>For his Eyes were bad by Candle-light, and Candle-light alters the ſight much:</hi> But when he heard him ſpeak, <hi>he could have ſworn it was he;</hi> Yet he did not ſay ſo, <hi>becauſe he was not ask'd.</hi> Here the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> plainly falſifies. For <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> made no ſuch Reply. Indeed the Priſoner tax'd him, that he ſhould ſay before the King, he had never ſeen him before.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> But the Clerk of the Council, though <hi>Mr. Coleman</hi> was very glad to ſee him there, ſpake not a word of this matter; neither did the Priſoner put him in mind ſo to do, though he were examin'd in his behalf, and that the point was ſo conducing to his ſafety. <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> therefore ſpeaks the Truth, and tells ye, he ſaid, he would not ſwear that he had ſeen him before in his life,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> becauſe his ſight was bad by Candlelight; but when he heard him ſpeak, he could have ſworn,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 'twas he; but twas not his buſineſs then. And this Sr. <hi>Thomas Doleman</hi> himſelf explains to have been <hi>Mr. Oates</hi>'s meaning, who being ask'd,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> whether <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> ſhould ſay he had <hi>never ſeen him,</hi> return'd no more then this, for the Witneſſes Anſwer, <hi>That he did not know him as he ſtood there:</hi> which plainly related to the weakneſs of an imperfect ſight, and not to the act of ſeeing a man at ſuch or ſuch a time. But all this the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51086:4"/>
                  <hi>Epitomizer</hi> wiſely left out; for his <hi>Compendium</hi> is an Epitome; and no Epitome can be an Epitome, unleſs it be an Epitome.</p>
               <p>With as little reaſon was the Point of Familiarity urg'd: For there is a great difference between the Knowledge of a man, and Familiarity with the ſame Perſon. A man may know a man by ſight, and yet not be familiar with him. Neither did <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> pretend to any familiarity with <hi>Coleman:</hi> He only tells ye, That he went to viſit a Friend at <hi>Mr. Colemans</hi> Houſe,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>Mr. Coleman</hi> ſent a Letter by him upon his Friends Recommendation, That <hi>Coleman</hi> came where he was,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 24. — 27.</note> to <hi>Wild-Houſe</hi> and at <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Chamber; and all this might be, where there was no ſuch Intimacy or Familiarity as <hi>Coleman</hi> pretended the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy requir'd: For it was ground ſufficient for <hi>Coleman</hi> to truſt Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> when he ſaw him in ſuch places, and in ſuch Company, and under the Character of a friend. And therefore, what Sir <hi>Thomas Doleman</hi> atteſted in Court, That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſhould there ſay, <hi>That he knew not</hi> Coleman <hi>well,</hi> and, <hi>That he had no acquaintance with him,</hi> might very well be true, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt prejudice to his Evidence, and is no Argument, that he knew <hi>Coleman</hi> no better, after his ſpeaking then before, as the Epitomiſer in the vanity of his Imagination fondly inferrs.</p>
               <p>The next Objection is, That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> did not lay any poſitive Treaſon to his Charge at the Council-Board, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To this the Man of Brevity, ſums up Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Reply. That he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd then to lay no more to his Charge; That he was ſo Weak and Tir'd, through his late Fatigue and Watchings, that upon his Salvation, he could ſcarce ſtand upon his Leggs, (to which <hi>his want of his Memory, as not having Conſulted his Papers,</hi> ſhould have been added) was the beſt anſwer he gave the Court, why he omitted the moſt weighty Matters, as alſo the acount of the whole in relation to the Kings Murther at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor.</hi> Nor could Sir <hi>Robert Southwel</hi> witneſs any thing new to <hi>Oates</hi>'s ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage more, then that he ſaid in Council, That if Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> Papers were ſearch'd, there would be matter found in them, that he believed, would coſt him his Neck.</p>
               <p>Now let the People examine the Truth and Honeſty of the <hi>Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</hi> For the Narrative tells yee in a fair Character, how Sir <hi>Robert Southwell</hi> atteſted, That <hi>Colemans</hi> Papers being found in a Deal Box, ſeveral of them ſounded ſo ſtrangely to the Lords, that they were amaz'd, and preſently ſent <hi>Coleman</hi> to <hi>Newgate:</hi> And being ask'd,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>36.</hi>
                  </note> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> did give a round Charge to <hi>Coleman</hi> or no? His anſwer was, that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> did ſay of Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> that he had Correſponded very wickedly, and baſely with the <hi>French</hi> Kings Confeſſor: and did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare further, that the fifteen Thouſand <hi>Pound</hi> was accepted for the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the King, and that five Thouſand <hi>Pound</hi> was actually paid by Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> to Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> upon which the <hi>Chief Juſtice</hi> made this Reflection, that it plainly appear'd by the Teſtimony of Sir <hi>Robert South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had charg'd <hi>Coleman</hi> Home, and that it was a full an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Coleman's</hi> Objection. What a ſtrange honour had the <hi>Compendium</hi> for Brevitie, to leave out all this! But by this you may ſee, that the longeſt Cloak a Jeſuit can weare, cannot hide the Devils Cloven Foot. While the Father of Lies ſtrives to trample Truth under his feet, his Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Hoofs, will appear in ſpight of his teeth. Nay, the very kicking and wincing of his Offspring Falſhood againſt her Capital Enemies, will uncover the Nakedneſs of her Sire, and expoſe her Deformity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51086:5"/>Thus has the Grand maſter of Conciſeneſs overturn'd two rotten In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrences rais'd upon his own falſe Abbreviation, <hi>That</hi> Mr. Oates<hi>'s Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt</hi> Coleman <hi>was a late</hi> Fiction; and that it was impoſſible through Laſſitude, not to tell the King of <hi>Colemans</hi> Deſign, had he known of it. It being the very judgment of the Chief Juſtice upon the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, That <hi>Coleman</hi> was not charged at his Tryal with matters newly ſtarted, but with the Conſpiracy it ſelf, as had been done before at the Council.</p>
               <p>Well then, this Gentleman may be a maſter at <hi>Compendium's</hi> becauſe he comes ſo ſhort of himſelf; but he can never be a Matchiavillian to impoſe, in his firſt experiment, upon the people whom he undertakes to undeceive. What ſayes the Poet?</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. — <hi>Theog.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>A Lye looks Ill at the beginning, but the End will have a Shameful Revenge.</l>
               </q>
               <p>As to the laſt Charge of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> of <hi>Colemans</hi> being at the Conſult with the <hi>Benedictines</hi> upon the 21ſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Priſoner reply'd; That he was in <hi>Warwickſhire</hi> from the 20th. to the laſt day of the ſaid month. and ſo the Evidence could not be true in that particular. But becauſe he had no one Witneſs to prove what he alleadg'd, the Court did not think it convenient to take his own word; and ſo that Excuſe prov'd a meer Chryſome or Abortive Birth. Neither does the <hi>Maſter of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgements</hi> himſelf endeavor to defend this misfortune of his Martyr, not thinking it ſafe, for Brevitie's ſake, to be dabbling in the Support of too many untruths at one time, leaſt all men without my help ſhould ſee his falſhood and horrid Abuſe of the Kings Cauſe and Evidence.</p>
               <p>As for Mr. <hi>Bedlow's</hi> Charge, the Abbreviator does his Office like a Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; for, becauſe 'twas but ſhort, He takes all in.</p>
               <p>He alſo ſaies, that <hi>Coleman</hi> made little anſwer to him, beſides proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he never ſaw him before: (which Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſayes is falſe, for he was often in his Company, but indeed, by the name of <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) which was as good as nothing: but indeed, it was a piece of Policy becoming a Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of State. For he ask'd him but one civil queſtion, whither He had ever ſeen him in his life?<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> and the Witneſs gave him ſuch a Satyrical rebuke, that the <hi>Man of Intreague</hi> (as the <hi>Narrative-Trimmer</hi> calls him) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately pull'd in his Horns, and never durſt give him one puſh more.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Abbreviator</hi> obſerving this eaſie Conqueſt of his Friend, for brevities ſake, reſolves to give his Catholick Zeal a Little Rope, and to etch out his Abbreviation, leaſt it ſhould be too ſhort, with a Politick Remark or two of his own. For, quoth he, with a Papiſtical ſtretch, <hi>there was never any of</hi> Mr. Colemans <hi>Family had ever ſeen him, which had been morally impoſſible, had he received and brought Letters as he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How he came by this Intelligence, Heaven knows, for 'tis more then his Original gives him Authority to ſay. But grant it true, he knows Mr. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> was <hi>a man of Intreagues,</hi> Plotters alwayes walk in Maſquarade; he was too politick to ſuffer the Inſtruments of ſo grand a deſign to appear at his Houſe twice with the ſame Face, nor indeed with their own faces twice together at any time; And I am apt to believe, that Mr. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51086:5"/>Aſſeveration might in ſome meaſure be true, That he never ſaw Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> or Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> in that Habit or by thoſe Names, for the Jeſuits we know go by many Names (as falſe men uſe to do); or to uſe his own words, that he never ſaw <hi>That Face,</hi> of either, that is to ſay, the Faces of either, as then they appear'd faſhionably adorn'd, and with the natural and Genuine Aire of their Countenances. By which, with a Jeſuitical Equivocation, he might ſerve his Papiſtical Conſcience.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, he is reſolved to put his Confidence upon the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-hookes, and to undertake, not only for Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> Family, but for the whole Auditory at the Tryal; too <hi>few of whom,</hi> he ſayes, <hi>could compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend,</hi> how Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> ſhould know that the Letter which he brought from <hi>Paris,</hi> and yet underſtood not, was about carrying on the Plot. Truly this might have been a Miracle indeed, could <hi>Monſieur Compendium</hi> have prov'd, that <hi>Mr Bedlow</hi> had at the ſame time loſt his hearing. But what a ſhameful Impudence is this, for a man to bely a whole Auditory; I mean all that were not a ſleep? For they could not chooſe but hear <hi>Mr. Bedlow</hi> declare, that he receiv'd the ſaid Letter, at a Conſultation of two French Abbots, and ſeveral Engliſh Monks; among whom, there was no other Diſcourſe, but of the Engliſh Plot, and Deſtroying the King. But why ſhould <hi>Harcourt</hi> call <hi>Mr. Bedlow</hi> over the way, for no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but to hear <hi>Mr. Colemans</hi> Treaſonable Expreſſions in the Height of his Zeal? Why perhaps, becauſe he was unwilling his Friend ſhould ſtand in the Wet or the Sun, — or for ſome other Conſiderations him thereunto moving. Would any but a Narrative-Snipper have us put ſuch an Impertinent queſtion as this to men of Reaſon? As if they, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they can truſt one another, care what they hear one another ſay. Beſides, 'tis well known that <hi>Coleman,</hi> as much a <hi>man of Intrigue</hi> as he was (which is one of <hi>Compendium's</hi> excuſes of the probability, that the finding of his Letters might hang him) was two much wrapt up in the Admiration of himſelf, to be either profound or wary. But there is yet another Riddle behind, (For there was never ſuch a <hi>Sphynx</hi> in Nature, as our <hi>Compendium</hi> Writer) How Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> could carry <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> a Letter from Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> Dated <hi>April</hi> 75; and yet Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Firſt Letter to him, was his Long Letter, Dated <hi>September</hi> 29. 1675? This is a Queſtion, 'tis true: But why Mr. <hi>Compendium</hi> ſhould ask it, is another Queſtion. For it plainly ſhews, that the <hi>Narrative-Clipper</hi> was careleſs of that Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he ſo earneſtly reoommends to the People.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> For Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> does not ſay, he carryed any Letter from Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> to <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> Dated <hi>April</hi> 75. But he ſayes, That in <hi>April</hi> 75. he carryed over a large Packet of Letters to <hi>Monſieur La Chaiſe</hi> from Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> wherein Mr. Secretary is not Charg'd to have had any particular Letter of his own, but only to have been the Hander and Conveyer of the Accounts of the Plot given to <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> by other men; upon which the Confeſſor, well knowing how deeply <hi>Mr. Coleman</hi> was Engag'd, thought fit to give <hi>Mr. Coleman</hi> his Sentiments in a particular Letter directed to himſelf. And ſo the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence began in <hi>September</hi> following. And thus the Riddle is reſolv'd without the Help of an <hi>Oedipus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let men of Reaſon but conſider, the lamentable, miſerable, pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſorry, inconſiderable, and weak ſhifts of Confidence and Fallacy, that theſe people are put to, to uphold the ſhallow Defences of their Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Diſloyalty; as if they thought to deal with the Proteſtants like Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, becauſe their own Religion, is a Religion only of Trinkets and Baubles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51086:6"/>But now the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> is at a wicked Loſs: the ghaſtly Apparition of <hi>Colemans</hi> Letters has ſcar'd him almoſt out of his Senſes. Thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are upon him as the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were upon <hi>Sampſon,</hi> ſo that he knows not which way to turn himſelf. True it is, he makes uſe of the Jaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone of an Aſs, but not to the ſame purpoſe as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did. For, inſtead of ſmiting, he falls to expounding, and extenuating. Inſtead of an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviator, he turns Commentator; but with ſo little Succeſs, that there is not one word of Senſe in what he urges.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he acknowledges, that <hi>Coleman</hi> acknowledged them <hi>very full of Extravagant Expreſſions,</hi> becauſe there was no way to avoyd it. But that <hi>he hoped</hi> they were not <hi>Treaſonable.</hi> Suppoſe a Fellow breaks open and rifles a houſe, Let the People Examine, whether it be a ſufficient plea, for the Malefacter to ſay, he hoped it was no Fellony. He Proſecutes the <hi>Mighty-work</hi> of Converting Three Kingdoms, and Subduing the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent Hereſie</hi> of <hi>Proteſtantiſme;</hi> Implores, and Sollicits Forreign Power and Aſſiſtance to effect all this, and <hi>hopes</hi> it is no Treaſon: Violates the Tundamental Laws of the Land, and <hi>hopes</hi> it was no Treaſon. But theſe, ſaith the <hi>Animadverter,</hi> were only <hi>Rhetorical Flowers</hi> to <hi>wheedle</hi> in <hi>La Chaiſe.</hi> A very probable Story. Men pretending to Senſe, ſhould be aſham'd to own in Print ſuch childiſh ſimplicities ſo ſcandalous to reaſon. The Commentator confeſſes, that the Court of <hi>France</hi> had ſmelt him out, for all his pretences, and knew him to be a Perſon of no Intereſt, a meer Epiſtle-monger; ſo that, ſaith he, Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> could not <hi>Dream</hi> to whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſuch a cunning Fox as <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> by any other means, then by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting him with a Rhetorical Noſe-gay. But what was to have been the effect of this Wheedle? To advance the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Intereſt — By whoſe Commiſſion was this <hi>Wheedle</hi> to have been managed? By no body's — only it was Mr. <hi>Colemans</hi> Generoſity to his Prince, to give himſelf the trouble. Briefly then, Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> was to advance the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Intereſt, and the buſineſs was to have been brought about thus — Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> was to tickle <hi>La Chaiſe's</hi> Noſtrils with his Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical Flowers, and then <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> was to have perſwaded the King of <hi>France</hi> to have ſent Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> 200000 <hi>l.</hi> to go on with the Deſign.</p>
               <p>In good Sooth, the King of <hi>France</hi> had been ſweetly gul'd, to have given Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> 200000 <hi>l.</hi> for a Rhetorical Poſie for his Confeſſor. No, no, — <hi>Mr. Colemans</hi> meaning no doubt, was juſt as the Court, perſons that underſtood the meaning of Engliſh words, expounded it; down right ſelf-ſeeking Treaſon; and if he and his Confederates had not hung together, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the ſence of them that defend their Crimes, we had been but in a bad Condition ere now.</p>
               <p>But the main buſineſs is behind. Saith <hi>Mr. Coleman,</hi> ſaith the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentator, <hi>There are ſome Expreſſions that explain,</hi> that he had <hi>No Plot or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to Kill the King.</hi> As how? For the Reader, ſays the Interpreter, may find Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> telling <hi>La Chaiſe, That the Labourers were few, and the Harveſt Great.</hi> Whence the Expoſitor draws this immediate Concluſion, that it was an Argument, <hi>that there were but a few concern'd with Mr. Coleman.</hi> Dear Interpreter, thou art fallen into the pit which thou prepared'ſt for another. The Argument for thy Client is againſt him. For here is a plain confeſſion, that <hi>Mr. Coleman</hi> was <hi>concern'd,</hi> though but a <hi>few</hi> were <hi>concern'd</hi> with him. That is, not enow to kill and take poſſeſſion. Indeed, the Crop of England is a great Crop, and <hi>Mr. Coleman</hi> I believe did want <hi>Labourers</hi> to reap the Harveſt of his inceſſant induſtry. Which made him ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51086:6"/>petition the French King to ſend him men and money to advance the intereſt of the King of England. And thus we have done with this mighty Champion ſo far as concernes <hi>Mr. Coleman;</hi> And give me leave to tell the world, that if all the reſt of the right writing Papiſts have no more Salt in their braines then this Zealous Epitomizer, I would abhor the Catholick Religion onely for his ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning</hi> Ireland, Grove, <hi>and</hi> Pickering.</head>
               <p>IT is impoſſible that there ſhould be any Truth in a Religion, when there is no Truth in the profeſſors of it. The Abbreviator deſies all men that can Tax him of being unjuſt to either party, and yet in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhortning of <hi>Irelands</hi> Caſe, he has ſo Knaviſhly conceal'd, for brevities ſake, the Material points of his Charge from the Examination of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that we muſt be forc'd to pick it out of the Narrative.</p>
               <p>The Charge then maintain'd by Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> againſt <hi>Ireland,</hi> was,<note place="margin">Nar. P. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> That he was at the Conſult at the White-Horſe Tavern: That one of the Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies was at his Chamber. That he was preſent at the drawing up of the reſolve of the Aſſaſſination of the King, and ſign'd it: and that he had laid a Plot with others to move the diſaffected Scots to Rebellion.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> All this the Abbreviator for his friends ſake, leaves out. For it was not fit to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the Heighth of <hi>Irelands</hi> Crimes to the Examination of the people. And therefore, onely beginning at the Fagg end of the book,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>60.</hi>
                  </note> he falſely repeats his being ſaid to be a <hi>Caballing</hi> (no ſuch thing ſaid) at <hi>Fenwick</hi>'s Chamber about a fortnight in <hi>Auguſt;</hi> and that on the Firſt of <hi>September,</hi> Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had of him Twenty Shillings, which was onely ſpoken to prove his being in Town at that time, and not by way of Accuſation.</p>
               <p>The Charge againſt <hi>Grove</hi> maintain'd by Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> was, that <hi>Grove</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> were order'd to make an Attempt upon the Kings Perſon. That the firſt was to have had <hi>One Thouſand</hi> 500 <hi>Pound,</hi> and the latter <hi>Thirty Thouſand</hi> Maſſes. That they accepted of the Terms, took the Sacrament, and an Oath of Secreſie upon it. That the fact was to be done with ſcru'd Piſtols, ſhorter then ſome Carbines. That they had Silver Bullets,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>19</hi> Page <hi>23</hi> Ibid</note> which <hi>Grove</hi> would have to be Champt, that the wound might prove incurable. That he ſaw the Bullets in <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June;</hi> and this was an unanſwerable <hi>and remarkable paſſage, and therefore to be left out by the</hi> Compendium. That <hi>Pickering</hi> having loſt a fair Opportunity, by reaſon his flint was looſe, was forc'd to undergo a Penance, and had Twenty or Thirty Stroakes of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. That <hi>Grove</hi> and one <hi>Smith</hi> had gone about to gather <hi>Peter</hi>-pende to carry on the deſigne, and that he ſaw the Book where theſe things were enter'd. And that <hi>Grove</hi> told him, that he had a hand in the Firing of <hi>Southwark,</hi> and that he had receiv'd, 400 <hi>l.</hi> for his Paines. Thus far Mr. <hi>Oates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> being call'd, confirm'd the Truth of the Entry book, and that <hi>Lang horn</hi> was Regiſter. That <hi>Ireland</hi> was at <hi>Harcourts</hi> Chamber toward the latter end of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> where it was concluded, that the Ruffians miſſing to Kill the King at Windſor, <hi>Pickering</hi> and <hi>Grove</hi> ſhould go on,<note place="margin">Page <hi>41</hi>
                  </note> and that <hi>Conyers</hi> ſhould be joyn'd with them to Aſſaſſinate the King in his morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Walks at <hi>New-Market:</hi> And that <hi>Ireland, Grove</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> were preſent, and heard the whole diſcourſe. That at the ſame Time there was a diſcourſe about Killing the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Oſſory,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Ormond.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:51086:7"/>But the Charge ſaith the Abbreviator, was ſolemnly deny'd by them all. What is that to the purpoſe? As if a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> vallued the denyal of a perpetrated Crime, for the Propagation of the Popes intereſt, any more then a Common ſtrumpet does to pick a pocket, or a Jeſuite to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear himſelf at the Gallows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mezeray,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, tells us, that all the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Rack could not force <hi>Barrier</hi> to any Confeſſion, till his confeſſor took him to Task, and open'd his heart with the ſame Key, with which the Jeſuits had lockt it up before. Should ſuch Traytors make Confeſſion of ſuch Crimes as theſe, when there is a Crown of Martyrdom to be obtain'd, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts would turn Atheiſts, and the Scarlet Pomp of <hi>Rome</hi> return to its Priſtine Poverty and Nakedneſs. No wonder then the dying Slaves are ſo induſtriouſly cajoll'd to perſiſt in their obſtinacy, and that the Living adhearents ſtrive with all the art Immaginable to caſt a vaile over the ſhame of their Mother the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> never more likely to run the risk of Ruin, then by ſuch permitted and cantingly juſtify'd Acts of Impiety as theſe.</p>
               <p>But the Epitomizer goes on. <hi>Pickering,</hi> ſaith he, as to his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, proteſted, that <hi>He never ſhot off a Piſtol in his Life.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Though Mr. <hi>Dudgale,</hi> has often gone a Fowling with him, when they were young Lads toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and hath affirmed, and is ready to be depoſed, that he was as good a Marks-Man, as ever he was acquainted with; which prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Pickering,</hi> and this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium</hi>-writer, a pair of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid deceivers.</note> But who knows what now reſolution and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Sanctification of his Arme and the Exorciſmes of the Jeſuites, in ſuch caſes as theſe, by way of prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, might inſpire him with of a ſuddain. Oh! But it ſeem'd <hi>improbable to the Spectators by his very mine and lookes.</hi> This is now the ſecond time that this little pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to Omniſciency, has undertaken to know the hearts of whole Auditories and Aſſemblies: but if he uſe it too often, it will prove the Mortality of his Confidence. <hi>Fronti nulla fides</hi> is too true a <hi>Proverb,</hi> that every Millener has it in his Mouth. And it is as probable as many ſtories that the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> tells, that he might be pitch'd upon for that very reaſon, becauſe he was ſo little to be ſuſpected, having ſuch a poor preſence; but I will boldly ſay, this was a poor excuſe in our Epitomizer, and that here he was at a hard pinch to excuſe a Traytor by his puny looks; then ſays the <hi>Narrative-Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Ireland</hi> affirm'd, that he was conſtantly out of <hi>London</hi> from the third of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> till above a week in <hi>September:</hi> This he labour'd to make good againſt three Witneſſes for the King, who poſitively ſwore they ſaw him here in Town at that time, by ſeveral Teſtimonies of his own; preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to move the Spectators Compaſſion, that he had not been permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſend for any more; though the Chief Juſtice declar'd, that his Siſter had leave to go to whom he thought fit in his behalf. But notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this publick lye, and that his Witneſſes ſwore with prepar'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and his own impious Imprecations, his own Kinſman Mr. <hi>Jeniſon</hi> hath ſince ſo fully clear'd the point, and let in the bright Sun upon their dark Concealments, that the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> had better have ſhorten'd his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviation, and left out his lift of ſo many perſons of quality, then have expos'd them thus by their Names to the publick ſhame of owning and aſſerting Falſe-Hoods. 'Tis a wonder that none of thoſe perſons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who could not want Money, eſpecially the Ladies who were out of danger, were not ſo kind, knowing where the pinch lay, as to take a ſhort journey to ſee <hi>London,</hi> and ſave a friend; nay more then a friend, a Ghoſtly Father, one of the Patriarchs and Conſcience—Cabinets of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51086:7"/>the Romiſh Church. But 'twas all one; they ſent a pittiful Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to damn himſelf; which was the ſame thing as if they had come themſelves. But how did this Proſtitutor of his Soul, dare to call Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> Knight of the Poſt, who himſelf was then reſolv'd to forſwear himſelf, before the Tribunal of Heaven? Now what have the Papiſts got by ſuch a Holy piece of perjury? They have onely ſhew'd us, how far the Impulſe of Bigotiſme, and the Confidence of Papal Remiſſion will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a deluded Conſcience; they have only diſplay'd the iniquity of their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents by the Iniquity of <hi>Irelands Exit,</hi> and how miſerably poor <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> is peſter'd with the poyſonous and Peſtilential Hereſies and Leud Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Romiſh Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning</hi> Hill, Green, <hi>and</hi> Berry.</head>
               <p>IT mainly concernes the Abbreviator to manage this buſineſs of the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundberry Godfrey</hi> wiſely; for if he cannot rubb it off from the Papiſts, it will ſtick as a Curſed ſtain and pollution upon the pretended innocence of their Religion, as long as Popery en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures. Now therefore let us ſee how he behaves himſelf.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> ſaith he, ſwore, that after the Plot was known,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> ſeveral Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Lords, ſome of whom are now in the <hi>Tower,</hi> had threaten'd Sir <hi>Edmundberry Godfrey,</hi> and ask'd him what he had to do with it? and he ſaid often, that he went in fear of his life by the Popiſh Party, he having been often dogg'd by them: but here the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> leaves out the moſt material point; He forgets to tell the people the Occaſion of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans fears, which was, becauſe he had taken Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Depoſitions, and had dived too deep into the diſcovery of the Plot. For Alas, before, Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund-Berry</hi> might have walk'd the Town at all hours of the Night; there was no body watch'd him, nor dogg'd him before. But no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had the Papiſts receiv'd the Alaram of the Diſcovery, and that Sir <hi>Edmund-berry</hi> had been ſo Audacious as to perform the Duty of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and take the Depoſitions, but he could not ſtir a foot without a a diligent <hi>Obſerver</hi> and Spie at his Heels; which double diligence and care of his perſon, never ceas'd till they had Acted their intended Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy.</p>
               <p>Theſe were Circumſtances too weighty to be repeated in an Epitome, eſpecially, it being the pollicy of the Narrative-trimmer; to lead the Examination of the People aſtray as much as lies in his Power. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made theſe willful miſtakes, he comes to Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> his part, who, as he ſaith, Swore; That at the <hi>Plough Ale-houſe, Girald</hi> and <hi>Kelley,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> two Prieſts, about a fortnight before the Murther, did entice him to it, ſaying, That Sir <hi>Edmund Godfrey</hi> was a buſy man, and would do much miſchief. The <hi>Epitomizer</hi> ſhould have added, and farther told Mr. <hi>Prance,</hi> that it was no ſin to Kill, but a Deed of Charity to the Church to do it. But ſuch mincings as theſe muſt be expected, in <hi>Popiſh Compendiums,</hi> which are the moſt exact <hi>Compendiums</hi> in the World, always leaving out what gravels them. He goes on, and ſays, That <hi>Green, Girald,</hi> and <hi>Hill,</hi> Dogg'd Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury Godfrey</hi> to a Houſe at Saint <hi>Clements.</hi> That <hi>Green</hi> came at <hi>Seven</hi> a Clock at Night to tell <hi>Prance</hi> of it, <hi>Kelley</hi> and <hi>Green</hi> remaining upon the Watch. But neither <hi>Green,</hi> nor any of the reſt told him whereabouts in Saint <hi>Clements</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund</hi> was. That a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51086:8"/>
                  <hi>Eight</hi> or <hi>Nine</hi> a Clock, Sir <hi>Edmund</hi> came Home-wards. That <hi>Hill</hi> ran before to give the Conſpirators notice of it, at <hi>Sommerſet-Houſe;</hi> and then going to the Gate, He told Sir <hi>Edmund,</hi> that two Men were Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling within, and deſired him, being a Juſtice of the Peace, to pacify them; that he conſented to it, but when he came to the bottom of the Rails, <hi>Green</hi> threw a twiſted Handkerchief about his Neck, and caſt him behind the Rails, and then Throned him, and punched him with his Knee on the Breaſt. But the Abbreviator omits, that <hi>Girald</hi> would have thruſt his Sword through him, but that the reſt would not permit him, for fear it ſhould diſcover them by the Blood.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>17.</hi> Ibid.</note> That about a Quarter of an Hour after, <hi>Prance</hi> came from his Station at the Water-Gate, and laying his Hand upon the Body, found he was not quite Dead, but that his Legs Shook, and that then <hi>Green</hi> wrung his Neck quite round: The <hi>Snipper</hi> leaves out, that <hi>Green</hi> boaſted of this particular Act, which his <hi>Compendium</hi> ſhould have Recorded; had it been for nothing elſe, but for the Barbariſm and Cruelty of a <hi>Popiſh Chappel</hi> Officer. But This he would not have the World know, for Holy Church-ſake.</p>
               <p>Here the <hi>Compendium</hi>-botcher adviſes the Reader to take notice, that <hi>Prance</hi> having related the matter of Fact in this manner, Mr. Attorney ask'd him on a ſuddain, whether he ſaw <hi>Green</hi> wringing his Neck? No anſwered he, forgetting what he ſaid before, <hi>but</hi> Green <hi>afterwards told him ſo:</hi> which words ſurpris'd not a few of the Popiſh Party. Why this it is to leave out the moſt material Point of an Evidence. For though to the firſt queſtion Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> anſwered, No; yet to that which was impli'd, how he came to know it, he makes anſwer, That not only all the reſt, but <hi>Green</hi> himſelf told him ſo, and boaſted of his Butchery. And then indeed <hi>not a few</hi> might well be ſurpris'd to hear a Popiſh Zealot ſo imprudently boaſting of ſuch an irreligious and inhuman Act.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> Reader, take notice of this; and what a Cheat this faithleſs <hi>Abbreviator</hi> would have put upon your underſtanding: and what prime Cameſter this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Devil muſt be, that puts his Braines and Conſcience ſo far upon the ſtretch, to defend ſo horrid and never to be parallel'd murther, unleſs among the popiſh Maſſacres in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when they rip'd up Women with Child, and the like. Reader, take notice alſo of a farther Omiſſion of this <hi>Defier of all men</hi> for Truth. For he ſpeakes not a word of the Punches that <hi>Green,</hi> like a merciful Executioner, gave with his knees upon the half breathleſs body, for quickneſs of diſpatch, which was in like manner confeſt and boaſted of by <hi>Green,</hi> and all the Reſt. Theſe were Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, Reader, with which he was loath to aſtoniſh your <hi>Examination,</hi> and might be therefore well enough left out in a deluſive Epitome, to ſerve their Church, and cheat the world.</p>
               <p>After his fooliſh, or rather knaviſh Remark, he goes on, That Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> being thus kill'd, they carry'd the Corps to a Chamber of <hi>Hills</hi> at Doct. <hi>Godwins.</hi> Obſerve by the way another ſcape of this wicked <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomizer,</hi> which is that Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> ſwore, that when he came down, as is aforeſaid, he found <hi>Hill, Green, Girald,</hi> and <hi>Kelley,</hi> all four about the Murther'd Magiſtrate, newly turn'd out of his Commiſſion after the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh way; and that <hi>Berry</hi> came to them preſently after. Well! after he had Lain in <hi>Hills's</hi> Chamber till <hi>Monday</hi> Night, they brought him to a Room in the lower part of <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> and then <hi>Hill</hi> ſhewed him the Body by a Dark-Lanthorn, <hi>Girald, Kelley,</hi> and the reſt being by. That on <hi>Tueſday</hi> Night the Body was brought back to Sir <hi>John Arundels</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51086:8"/>Lodgings, and upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> Night, they remov'd it back to the place where it firſt lay. (By the ſame token, that <hi>Prance</hi> coming as they were removing it, they were frighted and ran away, but hearing Mr. <hi>Prances</hi> Voice, they return'd again.) A remarkable Circumſtance left out, for Brevities ſake, by the <hi>Epitomizer.</hi> That about <hi>Twelve</hi> a Clock the ſame Night they carried it away in a Sedan to <hi>So-ho,</hi> and then upon a Horſe before <hi>Hill,</hi> to the place where it was found. That <hi>Girald,</hi> and one <hi>Vernat</hi> ſpake to him of a great reward, and that there was a good one to be ſent by the <hi>Lord Bellaſis.</hi> That in the beginning of <hi>November, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, Lawſon, Girald,</hi> Himſelf and one <hi>Dethick,</hi> met together at <hi>Bow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> where reading all the Writing of the Murther, they were very merry, by the ſame token that Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> being jealous of being over-heard, caught the Drawer Liſtning, and threarn'd to kick him down Stairs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bedlow,</hi> ſaith the Abbreviator, ſwore, that <hi>La Faire, Prichard, Welſh, Keins,</hi> and other Prieſts, did treat with him about the Murther of a Gentleman in <hi>October</hi> Laſt. That they ſent him to Inſinuate himſelf into the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury Godfrey,</hi> not telling him their Deſign. That on <hi>Saturday,</hi> the day before Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury Godfrey</hi> was Murther'd, <hi>La Faire</hi> met <hi>Bedlow</hi> by accident in <hi>Lincolns-Inn-feilds,</hi> and alſo at the <hi>Palſ-Graves-Head</hi>-Tavern, where he told <hi>Bedlow,</hi> that a Material Man was to be put out of the Way, who had all <hi>Oates</hi>'s and <hi>Tongue</hi>'s Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which, if not taken from him, would diſcover their Deſign to that Degree that they muſt ſtay till another Age to Effect it. That <hi>La Faire</hi> told him, he ſhould have 4000 <hi>l.</hi> for a reward; That no worſe, a man then my Lord <hi>Bellaſis</hi> was engag'd for it, and that Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> had order to pay it. That he then parted with <hi>La Faire,</hi> but came not according to his Engagement to <hi>Somerſet-Houſe:</hi> That on Munday night <hi>La Faire</hi> met him again in <hi>Fleet-street,</hi> and charg'd him with breach of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. To which it was anſwered, That he knew not but that the perſon to be murther'd might be his Friend. Whereupon <hi>La Faire</hi> appointed him to meet him at Eight of the Clock at <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> and he ſhould know more. That coming there, <hi>La Faire</hi> told him, that the man was Kill'd; and that if he would help to carry off the body, he ſhould have half the reward; and then, at <hi>Mr. Bedlows</hi> requeſt, he ſhew'd him the body by a Lanthorn; but that he did not ſee either <hi>Hill, Green</hi> or <hi>Berry</hi> then in the Room. But that he had ſuch a Remembrance of Faces, that he could tell all he ſaw there, though the light were ſmall.</p>
               <p>Here the Abbreviator recommends to the Reader a learned Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That <hi>Mr. Bedlow</hi> had depos'd before the Lords, as their Journals Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy, that he ſaw <hi>Prance,</hi> and that <hi>Welſh, Le Faire, Atkins,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Bellaſis</hi>'s man were with him, being quite different Actors from thoſe mention'd by <hi>Prance.</hi> From whence 'tis ſuppos'd, that <hi>Mr. Bedlow</hi> nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe, and <hi>Mr. Prance</hi> naming others to have done the Fact, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them ſpoke truth.</p>
               <p>What ſtrange concluſions does this <hi>Nicodemus</hi> labour to impoſe upon the Obſervation of the People. Obſerve then, Reader, <hi>Mr. Bedlow</hi> no way contradicts the Lords Journals. For he ſwears in the Narrative,<note place="margin">Pag <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note> that he did ſee <hi>Mr. Prance</hi> there, which was the occaſion of his knowing him again in the <hi>Lobby;</hi> and that <hi>La Faire</hi> led him by the hand, into the Room where were many more. But neither before the Lords, nor at the Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al did he undertake to diſtinguiſh the perſons that did the Fact. This is then a concluſion more juſtly to be drawn from the Epitomizer's unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Obſervation, that there were too diſtinct parties, that had it in their Pates, to <hi>put</hi> Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury Godfrey out of the Way. Le Faire's</hi> Party, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51086:9"/>
                  <hi>Kelly</hi> and <hi>Giralds</hi> Party. But it happen'd that the laſt were two yare for the firſt; and had diſpatcht their buſineſs while <hi>Le Faire</hi> went Hawking about with his great Rewards for a Chapman. Now when the buſineſs was done, both Parties joyn'd, and fed their Curioſities with the beautiful Object of a Murther'd Heretick, which is the true Sence of <hi>Mr. Bedlow's</hi> Depoſition, though the Epitomiſer would ſo fain have ſcrew'd it the wrong way.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, Then quoth he, He tells us, meaning <hi>Mr. Bedlow, That the Corps had a Cravat about the Neck like that about his own, but ſo ſtreight, that he could not get his finger between.</hi> Which Reader, ſaith the falſe Epitomiſer, was no very proper Inſtrument to ſtrangle a ſtrong <hi>man, ſo cleverly, and without Noiſe.</hi> I know not what Experience in ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or hanging this Defender of the Maſſacre may have; But that Reader who will not believe, that four ſtrong men to one, may be able to ſtrangle (by ſurprize) one ſtrong man, cleverly, and without Noiſe; and that a long Cravat is not a proper Inſtrument for the buſineſs, I wiſh him no other harm, but that he may never be ſo unfortunate, as to have the Concluſion try'd upon himſelf.</p>
               <p>He proceeds, that <hi>Mr. Bedlow</hi> knew him preſently, though to beguile him, they told him, he belong'd to a Perſon of Quality. That the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> then with him, were not thoſe, that had formerly employ'd him, to inſinuate himſelf into Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury</hi>'s Acquaintance; and yet <hi>Reader,</hi> his Worſhip inform'd us, as you ſee but juſt before, that his Introducer, <hi>La Faire,</hi> was one of them that ſo imploy'd him. This the Obſervator takes to be a Smiter, and worſhips Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> for putting ſuch a Slur as this upon himſelf. Poor Creatures! They are very thankful for the leaſt ſeeming Kindneſs, that might help 'em out at ſuch a dead Lift as this. As if it had never happened in this World, that a Man might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce his Friend into a Room, and go out again. <hi>La Faire</hi> had glutted his Eyes with the Shew already, and might be drawn aſide in Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with ſome other Perſon. And it is moſt probable, that they who ſtood about the Body, next to Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> were ſuch to whom the Fact was moſt a Novelty; and conſequently, leſs acquainted with Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi>'s Concerns. Now, <hi>Reader,</hi> where there is no Oppoſition to Reaſon, 'tis a meer Cavil to fix a Contradiction; Eſpecially, where the Crime merits rather Aggravation upon the Malefactors, then to be palliated with idle Excuſes. I would adviſe the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> to take the Murther upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to ſurrender himſelf, and be Hang'd; and ſo convince the World of Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi>'s Error, and prove all the Witneſſes Lyars. The <hi>Pope,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, might Canonize him for ſuch a <hi>Heroick</hi> Act.</p>
               <p>He goes on: Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> quoth he, farther ſaid, That he advis'd them to throw the Body into the River; which they not thinking ſafe, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That they would put it upon himſelf, and make it his own Act. That upon his ſaying, It was too early, Eleven or Twelve a Clock being better for their purpoſe, <hi>Le Faire</hi> Conjur'd him by the Sacrament he had taken on <hi>Thurſday,</hi> not to fall that night; for, that after the Diſcovery of the Plot, the Sacrament was Adminiſtred to him thrice a week. That he haſted away, and having ſo great a Charge upon him as the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he grew Diſturb'd, and went to <hi>Briſtol,</hi> where God put it into his mind to diſcover all; and ſo he wrote to the Secretary.</p>
               <p>The premiſes, ſaith he, were endeavourd to be prov'd by four Collat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Teſtimonies. <hi>Firſt,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Robinſon</hi> of the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, that Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> ſaid to him, That he believ'd he ſhould be the firſt Martyr. <hi>Secondly,</hi> by one <hi>Curtis,</hi> a poor Chare-woman
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51086:9"/>belonging to Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag</hi> 28. — 39.</note> (though the Narrative ſays ſhe was his maid, and entruſted with the Keys of his Houſhold Concerns) who Swore, that ſhe ſaw <hi>Hill</hi> with her Maſter about nine or ten a Clock in the morning, on the <hi>Saturday</hi> he was murther'd, which the <hi>Epitomiſer</hi> left out for brevitie's ſake, That ſhe ſaw him in the ſame Cloaths that he had on at the Bar; and that ſhe ſaw <hi>Green</hi> with her maſter a fortnight before. Now, why may not a poor Chare-womans Eyes be as good as a Lady's? Or, why may not ſhe ſwear as true as a Jeſuite's Miſs. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> by <hi>Hills</hi> denying before the Council, that ever he ſaw <hi>Gyrald,</hi> when as the Boy prov'd in Court, that they frequently met there. He might have added, the maſter too, who ſwore the ſame. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> by <hi>Berry's</hi> ſending away the <hi>Prince,</hi> while the Intregue was on foot, upon pretence, that he had Orders to tell all perſons of Quality, that the Queen was private, and that they were not to come in.<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> And then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ask't at his Examination by the Lords, Whether he had ever had ſuch Orders before? he then ſaid, <hi>No;</hi> which Contradicted his Anſwer at the Bar; where he affirm'd, he had had ſeveral of the ſame Nature: One of which muſt be a Lye.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Epitomizer</hi> having thus diſplay'd his Treacherous Endeavors, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Conſideration of the People, by ſlubbering over the Charge, and farcing it with the petty Dictates of his Papiſtical Malice, being come to the Priſoner's Defence, takes upon him to be their Champion, and makes open War, not only againſt the Witneſſes, but againſt the Judge himſelf.</p>
               <p>To this Charge, ſaith he, the Priſoners anſwer'd with all imaginable Proteſtations, That they were Innocent. And well they might: For they did not believe, they had Committed an ill thing. Men that were taught by their Ghoſtly Fathers, and convinced, that Murther was <hi>no Sin,</hi> but <hi>an Act of Charity to the Church of Rome,</hi> might well proteſt their Innocence of the Crime. For thoſe Falſe Doctrines were ſo ſtrongly ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited in their Breaſts, that if Denyals and Proteſtations could have ſav'd them, they ſhould have been as Cheap, as the Proſtitutions of Harlots amongſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their <hi>Stews;</hi> and nothing but the gaping Earth, or ſome immediate Judgment from Heaven, ſhould be an Evidence of their Guilt, ſufficient to demonſtrate it to the World. Had the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion been chary of her Appeals to <hi>God,</hi> and maintain'd the Chaſtity of Proteſtations, as ſhe ought to have done, ſuch Proteſtations might have been prevailing Arguments of the Proteſter's Innocency: But the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of many Ages tells us, that they have been her Common Pawns for Belief; And that ſhe has now been truſted ſo long, and fail'd ſo often, that ſhe is become an abſolute Bankrupt; not to be truſted any farther, for a Penny-worth of Imprecations. And therefore, to tell us of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations made by theſe Malefactors of their Innocency, is a Gullery, which the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> muſt not think to impoſe upon the Conſideration of any rational People.</p>
               <p>But he proceeds, and ſayes, That Sir <hi>Robert Southwel</hi>'s Teſtimony did not advantage them a little, meaning the Priſoners, in the Opinion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. That's a falſe Inſinuation: For he, being ſummon'd as a Witneſs for the King, to acquaint the Court with ſeveral Particulars about <hi>Praunce</hi>'s Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination before the Court, was ask't, Whether his preſent Deſcription and Accompt of Places, were ſuitable to what he then ſaid in Court? Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> reply'd, <hi>Yes; but that he ſaid then more, then he ſaid before at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</hi> In the next place, the <hi>Atturney General</hi> demanding, whether <hi>Praunce</hi> did <hi>heſitate,</hi> when he ſhew'd the Lords the ſeveral Places, in relation to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51086:10"/>the Murther? He anſwered, That he went poſitively and directly to all the Places: Till the Lords ask't him, into what Room the Body was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd; but that then, after going into ſeveral Rooms, he was in a great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction: Yet becauſe in that Confuſion, he ſaid, <hi>Thus far I am Certain, I am Right;</hi> the Chief Juſtice would have it, that his Doubtfulneſs gave Credit to his Teſtimony; ſince a <hi>Knight of the Poſt</hi> never ſticks at any thing.</p>
               <p>What Advantage this was to the Priſoners, the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> ſhould have more amply inform'd us; for this Formal Story ſignifieth nothing. For Sir <hi>Robert Southwel</hi> atteſts, that Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> was punctual, direct, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, as to all the Places where the Murther was Committed, and where the Corps was firſt convey'd. If they remov'd him afterwards in his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, to a blind Hole, and ſhew'd him this blind Hole by a blind Light, and he cautious of miſtaking, became more Conſiderative and wary then before; Shall this be any Argument of the Malefactor's Innocence? And therefore,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> the Concluſion of the <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> was Logically true; That his Doubtfulneſs did aſſert and give credit to the Teſtimony of the <hi>Witneſſe,</hi> and confirm it to any Honeſt Man in <hi>England;</hi> in regard, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gu'd, that the <hi>Witneſſe</hi> did not go prepar'd to ſwear right or wrong. Which, becauſe 'twas Reaſon, the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> looks upon it with a kind of Frantick Admiration. But, ſaith he, the Priſoners ſtrook at the Root: For <hi>Hill</hi> deſir'd, that <hi>Praunce</hi>'s Teſtimony might not ſtand good againſt him, (This was the wiſeſt thing that ever he did in his Life, could he have obtain'd his Suit:) For he urg'd, that <hi>Praunce</hi> had deny'd all, not only before the <hi>King,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Chevins</hi> atteſted; but before the <hi>Council,</hi> as Captain <hi>Richardſon</hi> acknowledg'd.</p>
               <p>But this needs no farther anſwer, then what the Lord Chief Juſtice himſelf gave; that His denial, which was not upon Oath, could not be believ'd, becauſe his diſcovery upon Oath was ſo particular; and that the bare denial of what he had Sworn, could not amount to perjury. Mr. <hi>Attorney General</hi> alſo declared, that while he was a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and not ſure of his Pardon,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> he lay under Suſpitions, Diſturbances, and Fears, which prevail'd with him to deny what he had Sworn. But he was no ſooner returned to the Priſon, but being convinced and troubled, that he had done amiſs, he begg'd of Captain <hi>Richardſon,</hi> to go back to the King, and acquaint him, that all that he had Sworn to, was <hi>True;</hi> and that what he had then ſaid, was <hi>Falſe.</hi> But this, ſaith he, gave ſeveral of the Auditory but ſmall Satisfaction, meaning the <hi>Papiſts</hi> that were there, conſidering, that a Jaylor, whoſe intereſt it was to farther the Plot, might eaſily, if the thing were true, obtain ſuch a promiſe. Beſides, not a few knew how he had been us'd, and what Groans were heard where he lay for many days together, as Mrs. <hi>Hill</hi> urg'd.</p>
               <p>Here you may behold <hi>Mounſieur Compendium</hi> labouring for Life. This Denial of Mr. <hi>Prance,</hi> muſt either be made to ſerve their turn, or elſe be Annihilated. But it can no way ſerve their turn, becauſe it was not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath, and therefore it muſt be Sir <hi>Edmund-Bury-Godfrey'd.</hi> And it muſt Die with Three Stabs, <hi>The ſmall Satisfaction of the Auditory, that were of the</hi> Popiſh <hi>Party; The Jaylors Intereſt; And the Torturing of Mr.</hi> Prance. It ſeems, he was Eves-dropper in Ordinary to the Auditory; or elſe the Captain of his own Gang, that crouded in to breath diſatisfaction upon every ſlight Occaſion. For as to his knowledge of the reſt, which were <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> he muſt bring very good Witneſs of their Diſatisfaction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Credit will be given to his Preſumption. And to give the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitomizer</hi> a proof of his Miſtake, and that this is a Tale of his own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51086:10"/>let him but obſerve that there never was any Tryal of the Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſince the firſt Diſcovery, but that the People were always Diſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, even to tumult, when any of them were either Repriev'd or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted. As for the Captain's Intereſt, I confeſs, I do not underſtand it. But I will appeal to the Examination of the People, whether the Lords of the Council would give Ear to a Flim-flam ſtory of Capt. <hi>Richardſon</hi>'s, or joyn with him in an invention of <hi>Prance's</hi> denyal, to promote his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. For whatever Tale the Captain could promote for his own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, was moſt certainly to come to the Teſt of Perſons not to be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon by the Keeper of <hi>New-gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then they ſay, He was Tortured to make him deny. And who I pray brings this Intelligence? Why, even Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s own Dear Wife. Who by her behaviour in Court, ſhew'd her ſelf to be a Clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Woman, that either knew not, or car'd not what ſhe ſaid. But he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who had moſt reaſon to know, ſwears nothing but Civility from the beginning to the End. Neither does it ſound like a thing probable, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould be rack'd in their own Chambers in <hi>New-gate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Prance</hi>'s own Reaſon, ſaith the Obſerver, ſeem'd <hi>yet odder.</hi> For, he ſaid, It was becauſe of his Trade, as fearing to loſe his Employment with the Queen, and the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> which was the moſt of his Livelihood; and becauſe he had not his Pardon. But why this Reaſon was odder then the reſt, the Learned Commentator does not determine; and ſo we leave it to the Conſideration of the People, who with half an Eye, may ſee the Shallowneſs of theſe petty Quirks and Shifts.</p>
               <p>The Priſoner's Plea being thus over-rul'd, and Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi>'s Teſtimony adjudg'd Good; <hi>Hill</hi> calls for his Maſter's Neice, and Mrs. <hi>Broad-ſtreet,</hi> who look'd to the Houſe, as alſo, his Maſter's Maid, in his behalf. The Sum of whoſe Teſtimony was this; That he was a Truſty Servant: That he never kept ill Hours, but alwayes came in by Eight of the Clock: That he could not go out afterwards, becauſe the Doors were lock't up; and that they were conſtantly up till Eleven at Night: That he was at Home on <hi>Saturday</hi>-Night, when Sir <hi>Edmund Godfrey</hi> was Kill'd; and on <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>-Night, when carry'd away. That their Houſe and Stairs were ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it was impoſſible, that any thing could be brought in or out, but they muſt know it. That the Room where the Body was ſaid to be laid, was not only over againſt the Dining-Room, but in a Room that had the Key in it alwayes; and that every Day they went often into it for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or other: and that the Foot-boys ſtaid there, when any Body vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited the Young Lady: And that there was but one Key to the Door of the Lodgings. Nay, the Servant-Maid, whom Judge <hi>wild</hi> commended to more care then the other two ſwore, that ſhe dall'd in every Day at the Door of the Chamber, and was the laſt up.</p>
               <p>In this Teſtimony, the <hi>Obſervator</hi> ſeems to Tryumph, as if he had got a Mighty Victory. But he omits to obſerve, how fatally the Young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy tripp't in her Story, when ſhe affirm'd,<note place="margin">Page <hi>55</hi>
                  </note> that the Family had never been out of their Lodging, ſince they came to Town; and being ask't, when they were out of Town? ſhe anſwered, in <hi>October;</hi> in which Month the Tragedy was acted. Upon which, two of the Judges told her,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> That now ſhe had ſpoyled all; and that ſhe had undone the Man, inſtead of ſaving him. Whereupon ſhe would have Recanted, like Mr. <hi>Praunce</hi> in his Terrors, and cry'd, <hi>Why, my Lord, I only miſtock the Month.</hi> By which it was apparent, that either her Devotion had ſtupify'd her Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51086:11"/>or that ſhe appear'd in Court, only to ſay what would ſerve the Turn.</p>
               <p>As for Mrs. <hi>Broad ſtreet</hi>'s Evidence, It was delivered with more Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, then became her Sex. For, after ſhe had deny'd, that there was more then one Key to the Lodgings, ſhe confeſs'd before the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>57.</hi>
                  </note> that there were Six or Seven. And in the Queſtion about <hi>Hill</hi>'s leaving the Doctor's Lodgings, ſhe had ſo hamper'd her ſelf, by ſaying and unſaying, by ſaying one thing, and ſetting her Hand to another, that never was poor Fly ſo wrap't up in Cobweb-Lawn, as ſhe in the Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of her own Story. Nay, ſhe had like to have brought her ſelf into the Nooze it ſelf:<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>56.</hi>
                  </note> For, upon her ſtout and ſtiff Averment, that the Key was alwayes and conſtantly in <hi>Hill</hi>'s Door, one of the Judges told her, That he would not judge her; but that 'twas very ſuſpicious, that if ſhe were in the Houſe at the ſame time as ſhe ſaid ſhe was, and us'd to go into the Room every day, but that ſhe muſt either hear the Body brought in, or ſee it. And another of the Judges told her, <hi>'Twas well, ſhe was not Indicted.</hi> So that, Mrs. <hi>Inadvertency,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Confidence,</hi> were both diſmiſs'd with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Rebuke of the Court. So that, the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s Query, Why the Judges inſiſted no farther upon the Point of the ſeveral Keys, was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they thought it impoſſible, there ſhould be ſo many Keys to one Door; but becauſe they took it for granted from the ſable Conſequence of <hi>Hill</hi>'s being abroad; and not believing one word that either the Young Lady, or Madam <hi>Governante</hi> ſaid.</p>
               <p>Other Witneſſes were call'd by <hi>Hill,</hi> as one <hi>Grey;</hi> who, as he ſaid, kept him Company from the <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 'till the <hi>22th.</hi> till Eight or Nine a Clock at Night, but knew not what he did afterwards; and ſo did him no ſervice. Others he brought to prove he was Innocent, becauſe he did not run for it. Which look't like a Comical Scene, in the midſt of a Tragedy;<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>66.</hi>
                  </note> according to <hi>Shakeſpeaks</hi> way. As for <hi>Green,</hi> his Witneſſes fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo palpably as they did, the <hi>Obſervator</hi> leaves him in the <hi>Suds;</hi> which was the fitteſt place for him to be in.</p>
               <p>After this, ſaith the <hi>Obſervator, Berry</hi> calls his Maid; who witneſs'd, That upon the <hi>16th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> at Night, her Maſter came Home from Bowls, in the Dusk of the Evening; and that he was not out an Hour, all the Night after: That he lay within her Chamber; and went to Bed about Twelve a Clock. All which might very well be; and yet her Maſter might ſlip out, and ſhe never the wiſer. But that, ſaith the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentator,</hi> which ſurpriz'd the People moſt, was the Teſtimony of the Three Sentinels, who Watch'd that Night from Seven, till Four in the Morning, at the Great-Gate of <hi>Somerſet-Houſe;</hi> through which, the Body was affirm'd to be carry'd in the <hi>Sedan:</hi> For they atteſted not only, That there came in no <hi>Sedan,</hi> beſides that which ſtood there every Night; but that none ever went out, during their reſpective Watches: It being impoſſible, for the Gate to be opened, or for any to paſs by, without their Knowledge: Nor did they Drink one Drop while they Watch'd, or ſtir a Pikes Length from the Gate.</p>
               <p>Let him not make ſuch a hideous Noiſe with his Three Sentinels; for there is but One, that we are to take Notice of, or that could be thought to ſpeak to the purpoſe. Now, this Sentinel did ſee the <hi>Sedan</hi> brought in, becauſe he was Awake; but he did not ſee it go out, nor hear the Door open'd, becauſe he was Aſleep; It being the Property of SLEEP, to Cloſe the Eyes, and Stop the Eares both at once
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51086:11"/>Which the Court, had they examin'd the Sentinel to that point, would have moſt certainly found to have been the reaſon of his deafneſs, and blindneſs at that time of the Night. For moſt aſſuredly, Let all the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomizers,</hi> Papiſts and Sentinels in <hi>England,</hi> ſay what they will, the Sedan was carry'd out that way that it came in that Night. So that, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Drowſie Teſtimony of Mounſieur <hi>Trollop,</hi> the people were ſo far from being Supriz'd with it, as the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> Fabulouſly Poetrizes, that the Malefactors were no ſooner brought in Guilty, but the whole Aſſembly gave a great ſhout of applauſe, to ſee ſuch Criminals as they, ſo fairely convicted, ſo near the puniſhment of ſo deteſtable a Crime.</p>
               <p>With theſe Omiſſions, and theſe Reflections, has our <hi>Parti Perpale, Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative-pairer,</hi> Half Obſervator, half Abbreviator, labour'd to the utmoſt of his Power, to Palliate one of the moſt Barbarous Murthers that have been Committed for many Ages. I expected from the <hi>Epitomizer,</hi> when he came to Annihilate this Murther, that he ſhould have huff't and ding'd, and fum'd and foam'd, and curs'd and ſwore, and bann'd, and ſunk, and damm'd Himſelf; that there was never any ſuch Perſon in the World, as Sir <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey;</hi> That there was never any ſuch Man Born, or ever ſhould be Born, as long as the World endures. Or elſe that he would have contrived ſome fine Story, Garniſh'd out with ſome of Mr. <hi>Coleman's Rhetorical Flowers,</hi> and have told us of a certain great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, at Court, that either out of Malice or Revenge, or elſe for Favour or Affection, or for ſome other probable Reaſon, had politickly caus'd Sir <hi>Edmund</hi> to be put out of the Way; and then thrown it upon the poor Innocent <hi>Papiſts,</hi> on purpoſe, that he might perſwade the King, to a General Perſecution of them, their Wives and Children, and beg their Eſtates.</p>
               <p>But to come ſneaking and peaking, and Crouching and Cringing to the <hi>Conſideration of the people,</hi> with his, <hi>How can it be ſo</hi>'s, <hi>and how is is it probable</hi>'s, that's ſo much below the High-ſoaring pride of St. <hi>Omers</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamanca,</hi> that I rather conjecture him to be of ſome Sorry Mendicant order, whom his Party will be ſo far from relieving, that they will rather give him a Saint <hi>Andrews Croſs</hi> Diſcipline, for attempting ſo far beyond his Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Where are all old <hi>Irelands</hi> Proteſtations, Imprecations, and bold Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monings of God to witneſs the Impoſtures of the <hi>Hereticks?</hi> Here's a murther <hi>Cravatted</hi> with a wannion!—They that could ſtrangle a Juſtice of the Peace ſo Cleverly, could they not ſuffocate a Murther more Artificially, and hide it with the Common dexterity of deluded Virgins? For now, by this ſilly Juſtification, it appears far fowler then ever. It will be impoſſible for a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite</hi> to put on a white Surplice; for it will turn Crimſon, as ſoon as it comes upon their ſhoulders. Since then all the Waſh ball-Proteſtations of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Malefactors cannot cleanſe away this unfortunate ſtaine, let it lye on— And ſo it will, as long as Hiſtory can utter to the World the ſtory of this Age. Certainly, Villany and Impudence were never ſo unluckily coupl'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſince the Creation. As if they had thought, that the whole ruine of their deſignes, had depended upon Sir <hi>Edmund Berry Godfreys</hi> Life; or that they had abſolutely believ'd, they had had the wiſh of <hi>Caligula,</hi> All the Necks of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants in the Twiſted Handkercheif, that ſtrangl'd him. But ſo Heaven order'd it, that this poor Gentleman ſhould fall by their bloody Hands, to awak'n the drowſie Nation, that ſcarcely would believe before, thoſe Impious deſignes of Popery, that threaten'd its Eternal ruin. Yet as God permitted the Murther out of his ſecret providence, ſo was he grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51086:12"/>pleas'd, Miraculouſly to diſcover it by their own Inſtruments, as Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as themſelves, till penitence and diſcovery had wip'd away their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and Seal'd their pardon. Nay, as if they themſelves had been ſick to confirme the juſtice of their Friends Condemnation, by a ſpeech formally penn'd, and ſtollen into <hi>Hills</hi> Pocket, they have plainly acknowledg'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to be accomplices in the Murther. For to what end ſhould they be ſo much concern'd to make ſpeeches for the Malefactors, but that they thought to purge themſelves by their dying words. On the other ſide, how ſillie and palpable a Cheat it was, to put ſuch ſtudy'd and flory'd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions into the hands of an illeterate perſon, that knew not how to manage'em. His own <hi>home-ſpun Language</hi> would have done bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and have been ſooner believed, then ſuch flowers of Rhetorick out of his Mouth. It was plain then, that it was not his own, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hand writing, by the Confeſſion of his Wife; and therefore being written by ſome body elſe, whether any overaw'd, and truly obedient <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> well inſtructed in the Arts of denyals, and mental reſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and ſoundly threaten'd by his <hi>Prieſt,</hi> do think himſelf oblig'd to ſpeak the Truth, when he onely ſuperficially repeats the Conn'd Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of another man, I leave to the Conſideration of the people. He that ſpeaks not his words, at the Gallows, promptly, fluently, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an unaffected and uncounterfeited Earneſtneſs, can never ſpeak from the bottom of his heart: and he that does not ſpeak from the bottom of his heart, can never be believ'd; eſpecially when he comes to diſcharge his Soul from the burthen of a Crime.</p>
               <p>What is then all this Florid Language for? For nothing but to ſhew the Contradictions of the Fool that made it. For here are Charity and Revenge, in a diametrical Oppoſition; while he makes the miſerable <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> upon the Hang-mans Stage, to forgive his Enemies, yet Cite'em be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nal of Heaven, for doing Injuſtice, almoſt in the ſame Breath; He withdraws his Recognizance, &amp; yet deſigns a proſecution at the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. So that by this double dealing with God &amp; Man: by that palpable <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> of ſaying he forgives, yet hopes, that God will not, he ſo ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impos'd upon a dying Malefactor, it appears moſt apparently, that the Perſon Executed, was Guilty of the thing laid to his Charge, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the reſt. Otherwiſe there was no need of putting their Friend upon ſuch a counterfeit, and obvious denyal of a Crime, whereof he had been really Innocent: And it was only a meer ſhallow Contrivance of Perſons equally Guilty, as being privy to the Fact, to repair the Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated Credit of the <hi>Romiſh-Church.</hi> For they cannot chooſe but know, what all the World knows, that Innocence never ſeekes, nor has any need of theſe ridiculous ſhifts, to clear her Reputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51086:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning</hi> White, Harcourt, Fenwick, Gawen, <hi>and</hi> Turner.</head>
               <p>NOW then, ſince the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> has been ſo unſucceſsfull in his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, to wreſt out of our hands the Truth of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi>'s Murther, even by thoſe very Perſons that were accuſed and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed for it, he can have little hopes to be believed in any thing more that he ſays. However that vanity over-rules him ſtill, and he runs on with his fallacies, miſconſtructions, and ſalſe concluſions as briskly as ever. Nay, he is ſo full of his little fetches, and dazling re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the Trials of theſe men, as if he were ſtriving to make amends for his former negligence and diſability in the weighty concerns of <hi>Hill, Green,</hi> and <hi>Berry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place, the Reader muſt obſerve, that the <hi>Epitomizer,</hi> has moſt corruptly and fallaciouſly, contrary to his defiance, leſſen'd and curtall'd Mr. <hi>Oats</hi>'s Charge againſt all theſe men; though 'tis true he repeats enough to convince any rational Perſon of their Treaſons; or elſe he muſt have left out the whole. But that is not all; when a man makes a promiſe, he ought to be as good as his word. For he leaves out that Foul mouth'd expreſſion of <hi>Whitebreads,</hi> which Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the bottom of his Rebellious Heart, <hi>That he hoped to ſee the Black F s—Head at</hi> White-Hall <hi>laid faſt enough, and that if his Brother ſhould appear to follow his Foot-ſteps, his Paſsport ſhould be made too.</hi> That he wrote Letters out of <hi>England</hi> to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> wherein, <hi>he hoped that it would not be long e're the blow would be given,</hi> and that by the word <hi>Blow,</hi> they had Inſtructions to underſtand the Murther of the King: which being all omitted, the ſum of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Charge <hi>Epitomiz'd</hi> by the <hi>Compendium,</hi> is only this. That he Summond a Conſult which began upon the Fourth of <hi>April</hi> 78. where they pitcht upon <hi>Cary</hi> to go to <hi>Rome,</hi> and reſolv'd, the Paper being afterwards Signed by ſome at <hi>Irelands,</hi> by others at <hi>Whites,</hi> by others at <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Chamber, that the King ſhould be kill'd. That <hi>White</hi> did about the beginning or middle of <hi>July,</hi> ſend from St. <hi>Omers</hi> Inſtructions by Mr. <hi>Aſhby,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ten thouſand pounds to be given to Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi> to Poyſon the King, and a Commiſſion for Sir <hi>John Gage</hi> (but he leaves out, that the Commiſſion was Sign'd and Seal'd by <hi>Whitebread.</hi>) That in <hi>July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt,</hi> he ſaw <hi>Gawen</hi> at <hi>Irelands</hi> Chamber, and that though he had ſeen Letters from the ſaid <hi>Gawen, giving an accompt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">p. 14.</note> the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> ſhould have ſaid, of the Affaires of <hi>Shrop-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Stafford-ſhire,</hi> yet he never ſaw him Write, till he drew a Bill upon Sir <hi>William Andrews</hi> in <hi>Irelands</hi> Chamber, where he Diſcours'd of the ſame things as he had given an account of in his Letters, which laſt circumſtance ſhould have been repeated by the <hi>Epitomizer,</hi> as well as the former, becauſe inſiſted upon by the Court. As for <hi>Fenwick</hi> and <hi>Harcourt,</hi> he affirmed, they were with <hi>Blundel</hi> and others, on the 21ſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> at <hi>Wild-Houſe,</hi> where lay before them Eighty pounds for the <hi>Windſor-Ruffians,</hi> and that <hi>Coleman</hi> coming in, gave the Meſſenger a Guinney,<note place="margin">p. 15.</note> (left out by the Abreviator, that from <hi>Wild-Houſe</hi> they drew off to <hi>Harcourts</hi> Chamber, where <hi>Harcourt</hi> paid the Money to the Meſſenger in <hi>Fenwicks</hi> preſence) That about a day after as near as he could remember, there was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51086:13"/>held by the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> where <hi>Harcourt</hi> and <hi>Fenwick</hi> were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and there they underſtood of the Conſpiracy againſt the Life of the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> by Letters from Arch-Biſhop <hi>Talbet,</hi> who deſired alſo Commiſſions and Money for raiſing Forces.<note place="margin">p. 16.</note> Omitted by the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomizer</hi> that <hi>Fenwick</hi> did bring Commiſſions with him to the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and ſent them to <hi>Cheſter</hi> by a ſpecial Meſſenger, and ſeveral Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by the Poſt, and that the next day <hi>Fenwick</hi> gave him Money, and admoniſhed him to procure Maſſes to be ſaid for the proſperous ſucceſs of the deſign: that <hi>Ireland</hi> being returned, Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> went to him, but was beaten and revil'd, for that the Jeſuits ſuſpected he had betray'd them, they having underſtood, that one in ſuch Cloaths as <hi>Oates</hi>'s, had been with the King; yet that <hi>White</hi> ſaid he would be Friends with him, if he would give an accompt of the Party and Miniſter that went to His Majeſty. Then declaring he had no more to ſay againſt the Priſoners at the Bar; excepting only that <hi>Whitebread</hi> offer'd 5000 <hi>l.</hi> more to the ſum of 10000 <hi>l.</hi> which Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi> refus'd, and greatly rejoyc'd that the Money was accepted, he ended with this, that he did not remember that <hi>Gawen</hi> was at the Conſult, though he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members he then ſaw his Subſcription; but he ſaid poſitively that <hi>Turner</hi> was there,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> (and Sign'd the Reſolve, ſhould have been added.)</p>
               <p>This was the Summ of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s accompt, the omiſſions being added, which had a very great Encomium from the Court, to be as exact an accompt as could be given by any man in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for all that, now methinks I ſee the Abreviator pulling off his Mittens, reſolving to handle Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> after a ſtrange Manner. This <hi>Malleus Haereticorum</hi> makes him beat and torment his own Brains moſt unmercifully. But he has hitherto ſo immoveably ſtood the violence of their moſt furious blaſts, that there is no fear of ſuch an <hi>Epitomizing</hi> Whiffler as this.</p>
               <p>The Charge being finiſhed, ſaith the Obſervator, it ſoon became very dubious, as to <hi>Gawen</hi> and <hi>Turner,</hi> becauſe <hi>Oates</hi> knew them not at their Apprehenſion,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> and his own words in Court make it good. For firſt he confeſt, that when he met <hi>Gawen,</hi> after his Apprehenſion in the <hi>Lobby,</hi> he did not well know him, being under an illfavor'd Perriwig, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to have a good head of Hair, he did not underſtand the Miſtery of it, and ſo ſpar'd his Evidence and informing the Council againſt him. Well! Mr. <hi>Epitomizer,</hi> and what of all this? It may be he might not know him in that filthy Perriwig,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> for it ſeems it was a filthy diſguize. But 'tis plain, he was acquainted with his Perſon, for he knew him to have a good Head of Hair. Nay, he knew more; he knew that Father <hi>Gawen,</hi> who had not alter'd his Name, though he had Proteus'd his Perſon, was the certain Man that gave an accompt by Letters, how Affairs went in <hi>Shrop-ſhire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> wherein he wrote that there was at leaſt Two or Three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound there, ready for carrying on the Deſign, and that upon a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Search, he ſaw his Hand to the Reſolve.</p>
               <p>Now for <hi>Turner,</hi> who had Maſqueraded himſelf after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in another kind of a naſty Perriwig, and lookt like one of the <hi>Furies</hi> with Snaky Locks, he ſmartly told him, he valu'd not Names, but that <hi>He was the Man.</hi> And when he cry'd, <hi>Did you ſee me at the Conſult?</hi> Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> reply'd, <hi>I ſaw the Man that ſpeaks to me.</hi> Now
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51086:13"/>what was the anſwer to all this? Why, <hi>Turner</hi> would fain have Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiz'd Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> out of his ſence of Seeing. And <hi>Gawen</hi> cry'd, upon my Salvation I am Innocent as the Child unborn,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> upon my Salvation I was not in <hi>London.</hi> So that the Court, ſeeing Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> firm to his Oath,<note place="margin">'Tis very true he was not in <hi>London,</hi> but he was in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi>
                  </note> which he valu'd, and the other proſtituting his Salvation, for which he car'd not a ſtraw, while <hi>Turner</hi> only proſecuted his Quirks and his Queſtions, was ſo far from being dubious of the buſineſs, that they declar'd that their Defence was nothing but <hi>captiouſneſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore Mr. <hi>Epitomizer</hi> might have ſpar'd this unſeaſonable piece of falſehood. But he knew the Engliſh of <hi>Veritas Odium parit,</hi> and was afraid of being under the laſh of the <hi>Proverb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Obſervator, for he is like <hi>Gawen</hi> himſelf, ſometimes one thing, ſometimes another, proceeds and ſays, that <hi>Gawen</hi> produc'd Sir <hi>J. Winfords</hi> Neece, and her Maid, where he ſojourn'd, who atteſted they were very confident of his being with them (beſides other Months) all <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> becauſe they did not remember his abſence, yet they would not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively ſay that 'twas impoſſible for him to be away ſome days, ſince they had no particular circumſtances in readineſs. But they and the reſt of his Witneſſes made it appear that he was in <hi>Wolver-Hampton,</hi> from the Third to the End of <hi>July.</hi> For then to their knowledge he was in the Spiritual Exerciſe. Which, ſayes the Obſervator included the time of <hi>Oates</hi>'s Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation. For by his ſaying <hi>Gawen</hi> was in <hi>London</hi> either in <hi>July</hi> or <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and then abſolutely agreeing it was in <hi>July,</hi> it in a manner follows, that the time in Diſpute, was in the latter end of the ſaid Month. Beſides that he himſelf ſaid, that he believ'd it was in the latter part of it. But when <hi>Oates</hi> came to be preſt with it, he flew back, taking the utmoſt extent of his Plea that he could.</p>
               <p>What a deal of Man-Midwifery is here, to bring forth a Shapeleſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, that has neither head nor tail? He himſelf confeſſes that the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes could not ſay, it was impoſſible for <hi>Gawen</hi> to be abſent ſome days, but only they believ'd ſo, becauſe they did not carry him <hi>Clean Linnen.</hi> So that their Teſtimony was not ſo much to prove he was not abſent, as to prove they did not carry him <hi>Clean Linnen.</hi> And indeed the Virgins Evidence depended wholly upon <hi>Clean Linnen.</hi> A moſt Obſequious piece of <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Diligence, to be ſo careful to provide <hi>Clean Linnen</hi> for a Stallion Prieſt. For ſuch a one he was known to be, a Prieſt after the Order of <hi>Martial,</hi> who Converted by the Muſick of the <hi>Epigrammatiſt's Poppyſmata.</hi> So that 'twas no Wonder the Women were ſo handy at his Linnen. Now, what was the Effect of this <hi>Clean Linnen</hi> Diſcourſe? Truly a very remarkable one: for it mov'd the People to a loud Laughter,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>64.</hi>
                  </note> and when the Lord Chief Juſtice had made his ſmart Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon it, they gave two ſhouts that made the Court Ring. But Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> more ſoberly made it out, that <hi>Gawen</hi> taking a Chamber to <hi>go into the Exerciſe,</hi> might pretend that, and come to <hi>London</hi> the mean while, and the Witneſſes not know it. Which the Lady had no way to avoid, but by affirming, that a <hi>Suſanna</hi> might carry <hi>Clean Linnen</hi> to a Jeſuitical <hi>Chamber of Exerciſe,</hi> and be admitted. Now why Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſhould be concern'd at ſuch a ridiculous piece of Female Putaniſm, wrapt up in <hi>Clean Linnen,</hi> as this, I leave to the Conſideration of the People. For as for his taking the utmoſt extent and compaſs of time, it was no more
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51086:14"/>then was Lawful, and what the Court allowed him, without the leaſt tittle of prejudice to his Oath.</p>
               <p>Now for <hi>Turner,</hi> ſaith the Obſervator, he inform'd the Court, that <hi>Oates</hi> not only did not know him at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> but call'd him there by another Name. There's no ſuch thing, he only ſaid he went by another Name. Upon which the Court obſerv'd, that when they had but one Name a piece, Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> hit it right, but when they had ſo may Names, they were too hard for him. But let his Name be what it would, he told <hi>Turner,</hi> that he was that man, and that he had poſitively ſeen the Perſon that then ſpoke to him at the Conſult, and that was ſufficient. And therefore the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> ſhould have conſider'd, before he made theſe ſlight Obſervations, that Cavils are no Defences. And I dare be bold to ſay, that there was not one of theſe daring Juſtifiers of their Villany, that ever brought the leaſt demonſtrative Proof againſt Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> but only ſuch as was uncertain, and continually trapt, or elſe confronted and overthrown by Teſtimonies of far greater value. Which the People, the more they conſider, the more they will find to be true.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith the Obſervator, Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> farther urg'd, that though <hi>Oates</hi> depos'd then, that he ſaw him at a Colloquy in <hi>Fenwick</hi>'s Chamber, yet by his former Evidence it was at <hi>Wild-Houſe.</hi> To which, adds he, <hi>Oates</hi> had nothing to reply, but that becauſe the Chiefeſt part of the Conſult ſat at <hi>Wild-Houſe,</hi> it was call'd the Conſult of <hi>Wild-Houſe.</hi> That is to ſay, he had nothing to reply, but what he juſtify'd at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> that he ſaw him at the Conſult of <hi>Wild-Houſe</hi> at <hi>Fenwick</hi>'s Chamber. Did Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſay he ſaw him poſitively at <hi>Wild-Houſe,</hi> and no where elſe? That was the point which Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> ſhould have prov'd. The reſt was nothing but captious rifraff, not worth a ſtraw, when the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial matter was prov'd,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> as was obſerv'd by the Lord Chief Juſtice himſelf.</p>
               <p>Now the Reader is to underſtand, that all this ſtir and Turmoil is to prove Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> Perjur'd; which makes me admire, that the Jeſuits, who accompt themſelves the topping Order of the Catholick Religion, and conceit themſelves to have engroſſed all the Learning in the World into their Societies, ſhould ſo groſly miſtake themſelves, as to err in the very Foundation of their Deſign. I cannot therefore apprehend 'em to be ſuch Bugbears as they pretend to be, but that it is only the fond opinion of our deluded Gentry, that cauſes them to throw their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into the Boſom of their Education. Rather I take them to be like our Splitters of Cauſes, who only ſtudy the Snaps and Quirks of Falſe Practice, but know nothing of the Fundamentals and Body of the Law: And that as theſe ſtudy only the Knaviſh part of the Law, ſo they ſtudy only the Knaviſh part of Divinity, that is to ſay, how to cheat and amuſe by vertue of their Profeſſion. Now then to go about to prove a man Perjur'd, before they had aſſerted what Perjury was, was an attempt ſo unbecoming men that preſum'd to Learning, that to uſe their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, they deſerv'd to be Hang'd for Fools as well as Knaves, for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo prepoſterouſly to work. <hi>Perjurus,</hi> then, is one, <hi>qui malè jurat contra animi ſui ſententiam.</hi> And there is a great difference between <hi>peje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, &amp; falſum jurare.</hi> For, <hi>Qui pejerat, is ſciens &amp; ex animi ſententia falſum jurat. Qui autem falſum jurat, non decipiendi animo hoc facit,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51086:14"/>ſed quia rem ita ſe habere putat.</hi> To the ſame purpoſe, ſaith <hi>Cicero, Non falſum jurare perjurare eſt, ſed quod ex animi tui ſententia, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cut verbis concipitur more noſtro, id non facere, perjurium eſt.</hi> Now Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> Swore that there was a Plot, and that ſuch and ſuch were Actors in it, as knowing it to be really true; <hi>ex animi ſui ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> but as to circumſtances, he only Swore, as believing them to be ſo, <hi>ita rem ſe habere.</hi> Their buſineſs was to have Dis-prov'd the Plot it ſelf, or that they were no way engag'd to it; but there was not one of them that did Defend himſelf againſt the Treaſon laid to their Charge, only by Denials and Proteſtations which ſignified no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; nay they could not ſo much as Diſprove Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, the Witneſſes which they brought, of their own tuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, either baffling themſelves, or elſe being, as I ſaid before, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by poſitive Oaths againſt them; ſo that it was impoſſible to impute <hi>animum decipiendi</hi> to Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> in Circumſtances, when the Fact it ſelf was ſo plain, and they themſelves could by no legal juſtifications clear themſelves from the guilt that hung ſo ponder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly upon their Shoulders; and was indeed in good meaſure prov'd by Letters of their own. Againſt which the Judgment and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Court over-rul'd all their Pedantick conſtructions, and ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Expoſitions, as being ſuch as could ne're be got off for their folly.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, they gave Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> Two violent Aſſaults, and thought they had been both ſparring Blows, for could they but have throtled His Evidence, then they verily believ'd their work had been done. To the firſt Onſet they Muſter'd up a Brigade of <hi>Stafford ſhire</hi> Papiſts, to prove that <hi>Ireland</hi> was not in <hi>London,</hi> from the Third of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to the Fourteenth of <hi>September.</hi> But after the Ladies had Teſtify'd for him with a great deal of Zeal, and the Gentlemen with a great deal of Raſhneſs, not only a Maid that had been a Servant to one of the Conſpirators, as has been already obſerv'd, came in, and confirm'd Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Evidence; but when both were again ſhaken by the ſolemn Imprecations of <hi>Ireland</hi> at his Execution, Mr. <hi>Jeniſon</hi> his near Relation, and when he Convers'd with him of his own Religion, comes and appeárs in the World, and to the ſhame of Lords, Knights, Ladies, Gentlewomen, and Inn-keepers, levels the whole Battery mounted againſt Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Reputation, and quite raiſes the Siege laid to his Teſtimony. 'Tis like he may hear of it, but he is of Age, and no doubt will anſwer for himſelf.</p>
               <p>To the next Onſet, they brought a Rabble of St. <hi>Omers</hi> Striplings, who proffer'd to Swear in <hi>Verba Magiſtrorum,</hi> if it would have been permitted, that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> continu'd all <hi>February, April, May,</hi> and <hi>June,</hi> at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and never ſtir'd all that time out of the Colledg, ſo that he could not be here at the <hi>White Horſe Tavern</hi> Conſult. However they brought their Scaling Ladders, fell on very briskly, and thought to have carry'd the day: But alas, thoſe Youngſters
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51086:15"/>were ſo far from giving Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> that <hi>Deadly Blow,</hi> which the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> ſo fooliſhly crackt of, that they were ſo vigorouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puls'd by a band of ſtout Evidence for the King, who poſitively con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted them upon their Oaths, and punctually confirm'd Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in all he had ſaid, that they were forc'd to a ſhameful retreat, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their Evidence behind them dead upon the place. <hi>Fenwick</hi> ask'd the Reaſon why ſo many <hi>Innocent Children brought up in a good Vertuous Education,</hi> that is to ſay, in that Seminary of Miſchief and Iniquity at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> ſhould not be believ'd againſt a Proteſtant Knight, a Proteſtant Miniſter, and a Proteſtant School-maſter, and Four more of the ſame Religion?</p>
               <p>To which Mr. <hi>Jeniſon</hi> gives him a ready Anſwer. For if ſo many <hi>Stafford-ſhire</hi> Perſons of Quality were ſo eaſily deluded, to ſtain their Honor and their Reputation, to ſave the Lives of Five Canting Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, Traytors to their King and Country, it is no wonder that Sixteen Boyes under the Laſh of St. <hi>Omers</hi> Diſcipline, ſhould be drawn in by fear or fair promiſes, to ſwear for them that could have giv'n them plenary Abſolution for a trick of Youth, had their ſucking Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſucceeded.</p>
               <p>To this, ſaith the Abbreviator, the Jeſuits gave a ſmart rejoynder, proving by the Contradictions that muſt follow, that all Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Evidence was a Perjury or a Grand miſtake. But the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> did not conſider, that all they ſaid was built upon a wrong Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that they could not be contradictions, becauſe they were not cleverly prov'd, as he perfidiouſly would make the People believe; but only falſly aſſerted: Nor did he obſerve, that while they were ſo ſtudiouſly Perjuring others, they were endeavoring at the ſame time to Perjure their own Witneſſes, and Damn the Souls of Young Men and Maids, Old Men and Babes, and all others obtainable, that came out of their blind and misguided Devotion, to lend them their Aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Now Readers, you that are the People of <hi>England,</hi> for it is to you that the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> makes his ſo frequent Appeals, weigh and Examine what has been already ſaid, and tell your ſelves where thoſe <hi>Innocent Men as the Child unborn</hi> did invalidate Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony in the leaſt. Examine with your ſelves whether they had any other way to juſtifie themſelves, than by the Subordination of their own Votaries. And that this may appear to be true, challenge this great Champion of their foul Treaſons, to Endite Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> Let him adviſe with his Councel, and Aſſign his Perjures. More then this, I will undertake that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſhall appear and go to Tryal with him by conſent in any Court of <hi>England.</hi> Laſtly, Examine with your ſelves, whether, if either the <hi>Stafford-ſhire</hi> Perſons of Quality, or the Striplings of St. <hi>Omers</hi> had been permitted to Swear,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51086:15"/>they might not have run a fair Riſgo of our National Juſtice. To whom I will only apply the Story of <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abner,</hi> that thoſe old <hi>Cinq</hi> and <hi>Quaters</hi> having a mind to have a little ſport before they dy'd, ſent for the <hi>Young Men</hi> from St. <hi>Omers</hi> to Play before 'em, for their laſt Recreation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Mr. <hi>Langhorn.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Epitomizer</hi> comes now to the Tryal of <hi>Langhorn,</hi> who was a perſon, from whom, as from a man grounded in the Laws of the Land, ſtrange things were expected; it was thought by his Party, that all the Paper in <hi>London,</hi> would not have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic'd for Panegyricks upon his Parts, and the Chronicles of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>havior. The opinion of his Intellectuals can ſo high, that he would wipe his back-ſide with a proteſtant Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> though all the four Inn's a Courts were upon the Bench. But for my part when I heard how ſimply he had driven his own Bargain for regiſtring conſults, and conveyance of Jeſuits Lands, I did very ſhrewdly ſuſpect him. Nay I found he was conſcious of his own weakneſs, to ſuffer himſelf to be decoyd into ſuch a Villanous Plot upon the hopes of an Advocate Generals place out of his rode, who might have mov'd in his own Sphear and have Stalk'd in his Collar of SS's, for asking. But alaſs, when he came to the proof, never did man pretending to Law and Reaſon make a ſillier defence, for he made not the leaſt uſe of either; as if they had both forſaken him in his neceſſity, and had beg'd his excuſe for appearing in his bad cauſe. As for his Plea, that he had been a cloſe Priſoner ſo long, and could not foreſee what the Evidence would teſtifie, it was extreamly frivolous. For there is no man tax'd of a crime, but knows the Subſtanee of what will be evidenced againſt him, as well as the witneſſes can tell him, upon the examination of his own conſcience. A perfect and clear innocence will ſhew it ſelf in ſpight of fate: and he muſt be a weak Judge who cannot diſcern the malice or intereſt of an Accuſer, which are the chiefeſt vermine with which the wicked hunt that ermin vertue. Neither did Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> bear upon the Innocence of any one of the parties Condemned. For then he would have accus'd them hand over head without diſtinction. But he charges one with one thing, another with another, as he knew they acted in their ſeveral Sphears of Treaſon and miſchief. Some were for conſulting and ſigning Orders, ſome for execution, ſome for regeſtring, and ſome for managing Forraign Intelligence. Which acts, as they were all neceſſary, for the carrying on ſuch a thorough pac'd Plot as this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51086:16"/>was (and that there was a Plot is plain by the Murther of Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munbury Godfrey,</hi> to which theſe very men that ſuffer'd were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, as contriv'd by their own Gang) who can be ſo ſilly as to think <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> hath done himſelf wrong, or believe them to be Innocent, unleſs they could themſelves have brought out the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that were really guilty; and that had been the only way to have invalidated <hi>Mr. Oates</hi>'s Teſtimony. It had been impoſſible for <hi>Mr. Oates</hi> to have borne up his head in the publick face of the World; to have ſtood the ſtrict Examinations of a great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, his Council and his Parliament; which implies all the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Judgment, and Policy of a Nation, had not his diſcovery been ſubſtantially true: which could not ſo have been, had he been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the perſons of the Actors. Unleſs there be any of the people ſo brutiſh as to believe, that the King and the whole Flower of the Nobility and Gentry of the Nation, were in a Conſpiracy with <hi>Mr. Oates,</hi> againſt a Company of Tatter de mallion Jeſuits and their deluded Aſſociates, who might have been buried among the forgotten Crowd, had they not like the firer of the <hi>Epheſian</hi> Temple made themſelves Famous by their Infamy. But for the ſatisfaction of the people, the Abbreviator muſt have his Face waſht a little, and ſo be ſent away to School with his Bottle and his Basket to learn more manners againſt his next <hi>Compendium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oates,</hi> ſaith he, charges <hi>Langhorn</hi> that in a Letter to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wherein he ordered Five pounds to his Son, who had been in Rebellion, and was reconcil'd to him again, by the Interceſſion of the ſaid Fathers, he expreſt his <hi>great care of the Catholick deſign,</hi> and told them among other things that the <hi>Parliamentt Flagging, they had a fair opportunity to give the blow,</hi> which ſaith, the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator, ſeem'd very odd to many, that in an ordinary Letter of Domeſtick Concerns, he ſhould treat of ſuch high and ſecret matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:51086:16"/>This looks like the Canvaſſing of ſome Catholick Coffee-houſe. Neither is it material what deſcants People might make upon Mr. <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; rather let it ſeem <hi>odd</hi> to all Men of Reaſon, That the <hi>Obſervator</hi> ſhould think to invalidate Mr. <hi>Oats</hi>'s Evidence, by quoting thoſe Proofs, againſt which the Priſoner himſelf made no Defence. As <hi>odd</hi> as it was, the thing was true, becauſe it was never diſprov'd; nor ſo much as any Reply made to it by the Party accuſed. Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi> perhaps, had a mind to conceal ſuch an odd piece of Indiſcretion, and the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> has here brought it upon the Stage to be publickly wonder'd at.</p>
               <p>He goes on, and tells us, how <hi>Oats</hi> depos'd, That he ſaw Commiſſions in <hi>Langhorne</hi>'s Study upon his <hi>Desk;</hi> when <hi>Langhorne</hi> appeals to all the Company that frequented his Chamber, whether any of them ever ſaw a <hi>Desk</hi> in his Study? What a Potgun of an <hi>Objection</hi> is this? The ſtreſs of the Oath does not bear upon the word <hi>Desk,</hi> but upon the ſight of the Commiſſions. No queſtion the <hi>Advocate General</hi> had a place in his Study to write upon; now becauſe a Man gives to this or that place, or thing, the general Appellation of a <hi>Desk,</hi> there muſt be a ſolemn <hi>Appeal</hi> to All and ſome, Whether Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> ever had a <hi>Desk</hi> in his Chamber? Well, if it were ſuch a diſhonour for Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> to have a <hi>Desk</hi> in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, we will allow, That there was no ſuch thing there as a <hi>Desk,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Logical definition of a <hi>Desk.</hi> For as long as the <hi>Commiſſions</hi> were ſeen in his Study, to which Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> ſaid little or nothing; 'tis no matter whether they were ſeen upon a <hi>Desk,</hi> or any thing elſe, which in a Lawyers Study might appear like a <hi>Desk.</hi> Here's a Catch indeed for a Lawyer to make ſuch a noiſe withall! He ſhould have appeal'd to the Croud of his Clients, whether they had ever ſeen any ſuch thing as a Study or a Chamber of his in the <hi>Temple?</hi> But to put the ſtretch of ſuch a proof as this ought to have been, upon the dubious Explication of a <hi>Nomencla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> was to ſay any thing rather than nothing, and to play at <hi>Puſh-pin</hi> for his life. As if Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> could have found out no better way to clear himſelf from having diſcourſe with a Man in his Study, and of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Trayterous Commiſſions</hi> in it, had he been Innocent, but by a ſolemn renouncing all acquaintance and familiarity with <hi>Desks,</hi> againſt which, it ſeems, he had ſuch an antipathy, that he never had one in his Chamber in his life.</p>
               <p>But now, ſaith the <hi>Obſervator,</hi> Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> (who was ſubtler then any of the Beaſts of the Field) began to be nice about Mr. <hi>Oats</hi>'s coming to St. <hi>Omers,</hi> &amp;c. Whereupon the Court anſwer'd, That all the Defences of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> lay upon Catches about time, a thing no Body could be poſitive in; <hi>which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>heartened</hi> Oates <hi>not a little.</hi> For he being preſently ask'd by <hi>Langhorne,</hi> When he return'd in <hi>April</hi> into <hi>England?</hi> anſwer'd about the middle of the moneth, and ſtay'd under twenty days; a <hi>Latitude</hi> which he would fain have granted him, by reaſon of his ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in the former Tryal, though the Court never then pretended (as you ſaw) to extend it to above eight or ten: And becauſe he fear'd Mr. <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne,</hi> he deſir'd the Court to ask the Queſtions, adding, That he knew the Court would be ſo kind, as to ask him Queſtions that were reaſonable.</p>
               <p>Here the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> is at his old Trick of Deluſion, and impoſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the People: For there was no ſuch occaſion that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſhould be <hi>hearten'd</hi> by the Court; it was Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> who wanted the <hi>Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizer</hi>'s Julep; who was ſo far from making any rational Defence, that at that very inſtant that the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> crows upon the <hi>Dunghil</hi> of <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne</hi>'s
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51086:17"/>impertinent <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> the other had nothing to waſte his breath and time about, but only in fiſhing, and angling, and pumping for an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that had been given to his Queſtion twenty times before in other Tryals. But the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> is offended with Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> for taking more <hi>Latitude</hi> as to his ſtay in <hi>England</hi> then before, which was by him done, by reaſon of his <hi>ill ſuceeſs in the last Tryal.</hi> Who but a meer <hi>Epitomizer</hi> would have been ſo ſhort in his Animadverſions upon Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, he ſhould have ſtood with a new-faſhion'd <hi>Tube</hi> upon the Monument for a week together, and have bellow'd it over all the Roads of <hi>England;</hi> He ſhould have publiſh'd it in <hi>Gath,</hi> and in the Streets of <hi>Aſcalon,</hi> that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> might have triumph'd upon the <hi>ill ſucceſs</hi> of Mr. <hi>Oates.</hi> This <hi>Epitomizer</hi> therefore ſhould have look'd before he leap'd. He could not chooſe but know that if Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had had that ill ſucceſs, he talks of, there had been no need of a <hi>Compendium,</hi> and he muſt have ſtudy'd ſome other way to erect a laſting Monument to his Folly, than by ſnarling, and beſmearing the Wiſdom and Juſtice of a Nation, with the inſinuating Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of a Trayterous Libel.</p>
               <p>The Author does not conſider that the aim of his <hi>Compendium,</hi> is only to deſeat that Evidence, and undermine that Perſon, whoſe <hi>ill ſucceſs</hi> has been ſo fatal to their damnable Projects. But if the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> calls it <hi>ill ſucceſs,</hi> to have his Credit juſtifi'd, his Innocence clear'd, and to baffle all the dexterity of ſo many imbittered <hi>Collegiates of St.</hi> Omers, <hi>the great Swaſh-bucklers</hi> and <hi>Termagaunts of Popery,</hi> I value it not, ſo neither he, nor any other, upon the ſame account, may have any better. However this <hi>ill ſucceſs</hi> made him ſo afraid of that <hi>raw-head and bloody bones</hi> Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi> that he was forced <hi>to deſire the Court to ask him queſtions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had he ſaid, that Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> was afraid from his very heart of Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> I dare truly ſay he might very probably have been believed; but why Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſhould be afraid of Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag</hi> 14, 15.</note> he had as little reaſon to affirm, and it may be leſs, than he had to hang himſelf. 'Tis true, Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> did ask Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> a long Caralogue of ridiculous Queſtions, that one would have believ'd he had thought himſelf rather at the <hi>Sport of Queſtions and Commands,</hi> than defending his Life. 'Twas expected when he would have asked him, What's a Clock? Or what the Sheriffs had to Dinner? There was never a Queſtion, as the People may ſee, that would have ſcared a Mouſe; ſo that when he had done, the Court rebuked him for his Impertinency:<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> his Defence being rather an abuſe of the Judges Patience, then a rational Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>But after this, ſaith our quaint Obſerver, <hi>Langhorne</hi> demanded whether he came with <hi>Hildeſly</hi> from <hi>Dover</hi> in a Coach, or on Horſe-back? To which <hi>Oates,</hi> after much Heſitation, anſwered, That the Queſtion was ſo ſudden, that he could not be poſitive. Upon which follows this Remark, <hi>That that ſame ſtrange uncertainty amazed many, but more ſmibed at it;</hi> conſidering that in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th he had reaſon for what he ſaid, as not knowing the Queſtion was caſual, but that <hi>Langhorne</hi> might have Witneſſes to prove now <hi>Hildeſly</hi> made that Journey.</p>
               <p>Now whence proceeded all this Mirth and Amazement? It was becauſe Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had ſworn upon a Tryal at the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> that he came with Mr. <hi>Hildeſly</hi> by Coach. To which Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> replies, That he did not ſay ſo,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> but that be came ower in the <hi>Pacquet-Boat</hi> with Mr. <hi>Hildeſly,</hi> and that then <hi>Hildeſly</hi> left the Company, and went another way. By which you may ſee what Company our Obſerver keeps, Men very prone to <hi>Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51086:17"/>and very ſubject to <hi>ſmile.</hi> Earthen Ware, all of the ſame tincture with himſelf; Queſtions ſuddenly ſtarted upon the memory of Man, may be cautiouſly anſwered, without being <hi>ſmil'd</hi> or <hi>wonder'd</hi> at. He that knew what Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had ſworn before, ſhould have fac'd him with his Contradicting Evidence; He ſhould have prov'd upon Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Affirmation at the Tryal, that, contrary to what he affirm'd, he did come with <hi>Hildeſly</hi> on Horſeback, and left it to his Jury. Elſe the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was propounded to no purpoſe; to ſtart the Hare, and tye up his Dog. Truly ſuch <hi>wondering, ſmiling perdues</hi> as theſe, might have ſpent their time better, than to lie in wait for ſuch miſerable Catches, and drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-mens Bulruſhes. It is impoſſible to think that all theſe men ſhould lay all the load and weight of their Defences, upon the weaker circumſtances of Time and Place; could they have any other way avoided the ſubſtance of the Charge. Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> comes and proves the Crime by circumſtances of another and higher nature, conſequentially depending upon the Fact, and againſt ſlight and ſingle circumſtance, brings Fact and circumſtance both together. To this, men bred up in all the deluſive Arts of pious Fraud, men profeſſing the Doctrines of Perjury and Equivocation, men acknowledging their Gang and Correſpondence, their private Meetings and Conſultations, their lurking up and down in their Boroughs of Iniquity, contrary to the known Laws of a Nation, and ſo bringing themſelves within the moſt probable verge of ſuſpition, think to avoid a Home-charge of Treaſon brought by one of their own Members (for they ſent for ſixteen Witneſſes to prove he was of their Tribe) onely by cavilling upon the difference of a week, or a fortnight, or ten dayes. Such things as theſe do but diſcover the Vermin in the Snare, and carry ſuch a Face of guilty Fallacy, that while men obſerve their doublings and ſhifts, rather to diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle, than juſtifie themſelves, they loſe the Reputation of their Defence. And it is not to be queſtion'd, but that this <hi>Obſerver</hi> or <hi>Epitomizer,</hi> which you pleaſe, has, by this vain Attempt, rather injur'd, than advantag'd his Cauſe; while Inundations of new and freſh diſcloſure, does but ſerve to teſtifie his ſnarling Envy againſt the daily Diſcoveries of Providence.</p>
               <p>But then, ſaith the <hi>Obſerver,</hi> he would not tell Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether he lay at <hi>Groves</hi>'s the firſt Night of his coming to <hi>London,</hi> or no; though he had directly ſworn in <hi>Ireland</hi>'s Tryal, that he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to lie cloſe at that Houſe; ſo that if he had ſuch Inſtructions,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ireland</hi>'s Tryal, <hi>Pag.</hi> 36.</note> it was impoſſible not to remember, whether he had broke them or no, and more eſpecially at his firſt Arrival about ſo dangerous and great an Affair. Here is now a falſe Reflection from a falſe Repetition, according to the cuſtom of Popery. For Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> does not ſwear he was <hi>commanded to keep cloſe at</hi> Groves<hi>'s Houſe;</hi> but that he had directions to <hi>keep cloſe,</hi> and therefore lay ſome Nights at <hi>Groves</hi>'s Houſe. Thus the Queſtion was idle, and the Inference as ſilly. For why it ſhould be ſuch an impoſſibility for a man to forget whether he broke a Command which was never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined him, is ſuch an illiterate ſort of a Riddle, that none but the <hi>Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizer</hi> would have ventur'd to own ſuch falſe Concluſions, from falſe <hi>Ifs</hi> and <hi>Ands,</hi> that may betray Weakneſs, but never aſſert Innocency: But now I would fain ask the <hi>Abbreviator</hi> one Queſtion, with what Face he, who takes upon him to pry ſo ſeverely into the pretended Failings of the Kings Evidence, and if he can but find the leaſt appearance of a Fault, purſues it with a full cry, ſhould dare to juſtifie that grand Error, if not foul piece of Knavery in <hi>Langhorne,</hi> to bring in the Woman of the <hi>White-Horſe</hi> Tavern,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51086:18"/>to make her ſelf the Laughter and Contempt of a Publick Court of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>46.</hi>
                  </note> only to do him an unprofitable piece of ſervice. The Womans Carriage and Preamble to her Story, ſhew'd ſhe came, if a Papiſt, with a prepared Zeal; if a Proteſtant, with a kind Devotion: And the Reflection of the Court was too ſevere for Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi>'s Reputation; that a Womans being ſo peremptory in what ſtanders by knew to be falſe, made the Contradiction in one thing,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> to give a ſuſpition that all Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi>'s Witneſſes might be as falſe in all the reſt. Nor had <hi>Langhorne</hi> any thing to ſay for himſelf, but that he hoped the Court, nor the Jury, would reflect upon him for it. Thus they will give an Ell to their own Teſtimonies, but will not allow an Inch to the King's. His Witneſſes muſt be all Saints with the memories of Angels, to ſwear to a Barley-corn of place, and a minute of time, or elſe be forſworn: Theirs may ſwear Up-hill and Down-hill, be caught in ſpeaking Falſhood, be ſham'd and diſgrac'd for ſo doing, and they that produce 'em, ſhall have the confidence to hope, that neither Court nor Jury will think the worſe of 'em for it. So then, this is rather to be wonder'd at by <hi>many,</hi> and ſmil'd at too, then any of the <hi>Epitomizers</hi> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Parables; that Mr. <hi>Langhorne</hi> ſhould venture his own Life, and the Credit of all his Witneſſes, in ſuch a Female Bottom as this, as if no Body had ever known the <hi>White-Horſe</hi> Tavern in the <hi>Strand.</hi> Had he drank leſs Water, and more Wine, 'tis probable he might either have had no occaſion for the Woman of the <hi>White-Horſe,</hi> or have known the Tavern better. The Court told him poſitively, the Woman had been very unfortunate in her Teſtimony; and the People of <hi>England,</hi> are to believe the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> before ever a <hi>Compendium Scribler</hi> in the world. Let us wonder then at nothing, but that Oaths and Teſtimonies, which are the chiefeſt Bonds and Tyes of Humane Society, and the Soul of Juſtice, ſo inviolable among the ancient Heathen and modern Turks, ſhould be of ſo little value in a Religion which accounts it ſelf the moſt ancient and moſt perfect at this time profeſs'd under the Canopy of Heaven.</p>
               <p>He is ſo fond, as to bring his <hi>Squabs</hi> of St. <hi>Omers</hi> again upon the Stage; but in regard they were no more believ'd then they were the day before, let what has been already ſaid of them in the former Tryal ſuffice, againſt a company of Boys bred up at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> ſent hither of an Errand to to ſerve the Catholick Cauſe, and poſitive in nothing but what concern'd the advantage of the Priſoner, which is the ſhort Hiſtory of the Springalls of St. <hi>Omers.</hi> Certainly St. <hi>Omers</hi> was a very foul Neſt, a moſt filthy Den of contagious Jeſuitiſm, that there were not ſo many as two that could with ſafety be ſent for, men of Age and Reputation, but they muſt ſend for their Gigg and Town top Teſtimonies, to diſprove an Evidence for the King, in a Treaſon of the higheſt Nature that has been acted for many Ages. But there are thoſe misfortunes that befall Treaſon and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which all the Policy of Jeſuitiſm, nor all the Fineſs of <hi>Rome</hi> can prevent. And that is not the leaſt of the misfortunes that befell theſe Traytors and Murderers; that after their not being able to make any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Defence for themſelves, after they had ſuffer'd for their Crimes, they ſhould be tryed over again by the faint and carping Obſervations of a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium,</hi> that inſtead of vailing, has only farther diſcover'd their ſhame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51086:18"/>
               <head>Concerning Sir <hi>George Wakeman</hi>'s Tryal, <hi>Corker,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>BUT now enter the <hi>Famous Tryal</hi> of Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> and enter Monſieur <hi>Compendium</hi> with a Battoon in his hand, like one of the Marſhals of a City Company, ſtrutting and laying about him in every <hi>Page,</hi> as if he had got a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from <hi>Paolo d'Oliva,</hi> to ſhew no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: ſo then the Reader is to obſerve the effects of more Joy, and more Brandy. Here it was, ſaith he, that the King's Council admoniſhed the Priſoners, That it would behoove them to take Notes, (<hi>as if, Reader,</hi> Hector <hi>himſelf, with all his gods, were at hand.</hi>) I promis'd the Reader a flaſh of Exultation from him, and here he has it. But who theſe <hi>Hectors gods</hi> were, I do not well underſtand; ſurely he muſt be beholding to ſome old Ballad for this piece of Learning. For <hi>Hector</hi>'s dear Siſter, <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> ſpeaks not a word of any ſuch company that ever he kept in his life. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> ſays too, that the gods divided themſelves, and that ſome took part with the <hi>Trojans,</hi> and ſome with the <hi>Greeks.</hi> But theſe could be none of the <hi>Compendium Hector and his gods,</hi> for <hi>Homer</hi>'s <hi>Hector and gods</hi> were moſt ſhamefully beaten. But what terrible Toryrories this <hi>Hector and his gods</hi> ſhould be, unleſs they ſhould be the four <hi>Windſor Ruffians,</hi> I leave to the conſideration of the People. And ſo much for <hi>Hector and his gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this frightful Advice being given to the Priſoners, <hi>Oates,</hi> ſaith he, was call'd, who began the firſt Onſet with the moſt <hi>ſtupendous circumſtance</hi> that ever was heard of, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Aſhby</hi> arriving here ill from St. <hi>Omers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> Sir <hi>George</hi> wrote him a Letter of Inſtructions how to order himſelf before he went, and when he was at the <hi>Bath;</hi> which were, to take a Pint of Milk every morning and night, and an hundred ſtroaks of the Pump. In which Letter, Sir <hi>George</hi> wrote, that the Queen would aſſiſt him to poyſon the King. Then <hi>Oates</hi> proceeded, ſaying, That he knew this to be Sir <hi>Georges</hi> hand, by another Letter a day or two after, which could not but be his, for Sir <hi>George</hi> had it before him in a writing poſture; that he ſaw him lay by the Pen, and found the Ink not yet dry, nor was there any body elſe to write, Mr. <hi>Aſhby</hi> being lame of both hands. I know not how the <hi>Abbreviator</hi> would have Epitomiz'd his Charge, had he been to have brought it. But if this be not a Charge ſubſtantial enough, and propt by ſufficient circumſtances, I appeal to the conſideration of the People, unleſs the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> have any new definition for Treaſon. Now what was Sir <hi>Georges</hi> Defence? Firſt he brings an <hi>Apothecary</hi> to teſtifie, that there was a Letter ſent to the <hi>Bath</hi> to <hi>Thimbleby,</hi> alias <hi>Aſhby,</hi> with Phyſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, without any name, neither was it Sir <hi>Georges</hi> hand, and was, it ſeems, dictated to his Man. But alas this was not the Letter which Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> meant. And it was the Chief Juſtices Opinion then, though with ſome more than ordinary Obſervations of <hi>Ifs,</hi> and <hi>Ands,</hi> and Cautions to the Jury, that <hi>Chapman</hi> did not anſwer Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Teſtimony; and that if Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> did ſwear true, Sir <hi>George</hi> did write another Letter. Sir <hi>Georges</hi> Reply, was to make that improbable, in regard it was ridiculous to preſcribe milk. To which Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> made Anſwer, That the directions for milk were to be obſerved before the uſe of the waters. And Sir <hi>Robert Atkins</hi> came clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, affirming, That it was but a piece of Paper, and that it was not to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51086:19"/>be offer'd in Evidence. Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> poſitively ſtood to his Charge, and ſwore that was not the Letter that he ſaw. Which Sir <hi>George</hi> to avoid, deſired the Court to take notice, that it was not probable he ſhould write two Letters for the ſame directions: A kindneſs that the Chief Juſtice was very willing to gratifie him in, and preſently recommended his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Jury accordingly. Though at the ſame time Judge <hi>Pember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> obſerved, that <hi>one</hi> of the Letters might be <hi>written to ſerve a turn.</hi> After this, Sir <hi>George</hi> call'd two Witneſſes more, to prove the writing of the dictated Letter, which the Court were apt to believe was true as they ſaid; but that was not the Letter in controverſie, neither had Sir <hi>George</hi> any defence againſt it, but only the bare denial of writing it. So that the <hi>Compendium Scribler</hi>'s Story about the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> and the <hi>Mard,</hi> and the <hi>Man,</hi> is all but twittle twattle, like an <hi>Apothecary,</hi> to no purpoſe in the earth. And therefore let this vain <hi>Vindicator of Blood and Treaſon</hi> moyle his heart out, the <hi>People</hi> are to know, that there never was a charge ſo fairly made and proved by one Oath, nor ever a worſe Defence made by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</p>
               <p>The next Charge is, That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> heard <hi>Aſhby</hi> talk to him of the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> he had received to be Phyſician to the Army; Nay, ſwore he ſaw the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> in Sir <hi>Georges</hi> hand. To which I do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd, that Sir <hi>George</hi> made any defence at all. Which was the reaſon perhaps, that the Chief Juſtice left it out, till he was put in mind of it by Sir <hi>Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Charge upon the <hi>Queen,</hi> the <hi>Obſervator</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Reader, that he may eaſily imagine how ridiculous this ſtuff ſeem'd to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> That a Lady eminent in Virtue, ſhould not only make ſuch a Declaration in a Public Conſult, but alſo in the hearing of ſuch a pitiful Wretch as <hi>Oates, who could help neither Her, nor any Body elſe in any Part of the Plot, more then the first Kennel Raker he meeteth with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know not how ridiculous this <hi>ſtuff</hi> might ſeem to this <hi>Emmet</hi> of a <hi>Scribler,</hi> neither is it material; but certainly never did the People ſo openly exclaim againſt the Carriage of any Tryal, as they did at this. Which Exclamation or rather Indignation of the People would never have been ſo general, had they thought what the Witneſs ſaid to have been ſuch <hi>ridiculous ſtuff,</hi> as this <hi>Varniſher of Conſpiracy</hi> ſtrives to inclucate. And therefore for his <hi>Billingſgate</hi> Argument <hi>of pitiful Wretch, and Kennel-Raker,</hi> for upon thoſe two Pillars lies the ſtreſs of his Induction, let him take notice that none but ſuch a <hi>Compendium Scribler</hi> would uſe the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or none but Fools and Knaves believe his Syllogiſm in <hi>Barbara.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing charged, is the proffer of 10000 <hi>l.</hi> for poyſoning of the King, which was not accepted, as being too little; but that upon the addition of 5000 <hi>l.</hi> more, the Bargain was made, and five thouſand of the ten, paid in part, and receiv'd. For proof of this Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> depoſes, That he ſaw the Entry Book, wherein was firſt, <hi>Memorandum, ſuch a day</hi> 15000 <hi>l. was propoſed to Sir</hi> George Wakeman, <hi>and accepted.</hi> And then underneath was written a Receipt in theſe words, <hi>Received then in part of this</hi> 15000 <hi>l. by order of</hi> Edward Coleman, 5000 <hi>l. of Father</hi> Harcourt. George Wakeman.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now, Reader,</hi> ſaith the Epitomizer, <hi>He that can ſwallow ſuch a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or ſuch unneceſſary and unheard of Entries and Memorandums, let him never for the future think any thing either Romantic or Sottiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, Reader, what can be more unqueſtionable, but that ſuch <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randums</hi> and <hi>Regiſters</hi> were kept? For they that had the diſpoſal of ſuch
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51086:19"/>Sums of money, muſt certainly, had their deſign ſucceeded, have given an Accompt of their Stewardſhip. It was a <hi>Sottiſh</hi> thing to undertake ſuch a Plot, but when they had once undertaken it, there was nothing that look'd either like <hi>Romantic</hi> or <hi>Sottiſh,</hi> to preſerve the memory of their Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions. Nay, had they reap'd the Fruits of their Labors, they would have glory'd in what the <hi>Compendium</hi> calls <hi>Romantic</hi> and <hi>Sottiſh,</hi> to have ſeen their Monumental hands affix'd to <hi>Reſolves</hi> and <hi>Memorandums,</hi> as Teſtimonies to Poſterity, of their daily Merit and Diligence. Neither could ſo great a Deſign be carried on for ſo many Years, without ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Regiſters; it being impoſſible, in caſe of Mortality, for ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Counſels to act methodically, as the Nature of ſo high a Concern re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd without 'em; only becauſe the Jeſuites were more prudent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal their Important Regiſter, the thing it ſelf muſt be a <hi>Romance.</hi> He may as well tell us there was no <hi>Plot,</hi> which he that believes from the ſilly Inſinuations of his <hi>Compendium,</hi> muſt make an abſolute Renunciation of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
               <p>But what ſays Sir <hi>George</hi> to all this? He makes no Exception to the Regiſter. The ſtreſs of Sir <hi>George</hi>'s Objection lay in this, <hi>That the Charge of the King's Evidence was not ſo ample before the</hi> Lords <hi>of the</hi> Council, <hi>as at the Bar of</hi> Oyer <hi>and</hi> Terminer.</p>
               <p>To which the Anſwer of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was very fair and probable, and the Reaſons of that Omiſſion were altogether as credibly balanced in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, as the Averment againſt him; the truth of which, I think, has been made appear, ſomething to the uneaſie inconvenience of the Gentleman. He was ſworn to be in as weak and feeble a condition as ever any man was ſeen in, being tir'd by public and eminent Service; and therefore there was no ſuch reaſon to aggravate, contrary to former cuſtom, ſuch a worſhipful <hi>Objection</hi> to ſuch an egregious height, as if it had been done on purpoſe, to throw ſhame and diſgrace upon deſert, and make way for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable Compaſſion.</p>
               <p>Now then to confirm Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Teſtimony, and that if he had been remiſs before, it was only the Failure of his faint and feeble condition of Body, Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> ſwore, that upon the delivery of a Bill of 2000 <hi>l.</hi> by <hi>Harcourt,</hi> and promiſe of the reſt in due time; and upon farther diſcourſe, <hi>Harcourt</hi> told Sir <hi>George, That the Buſineſs must be well follow'd and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, becauſe ſo much depended upon it. For if we ſhould miſs to Kill Him at</hi> Windſor, <hi>and you miſs your way, which we hope you will not, we will do it at</hi> Newmarket.</p>
               <p>Here the Chief Juſtice made a Heſitation, ſaying, <hi>He ſaid quite another thing then he ſaid before;</hi> till the Lord <hi>North,</hi> Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> and Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Sawyer</hi> unanimouſly anſwer'd, <hi>No, he ſaid the ſame before.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon demanding, What was Sir <hi>George</hi>'s Anſwer? He reply'd, that Sir <hi>George</hi>'s Anſwer was, <hi>If I find you ready, I will be ready in all things;</hi> And that this was all a continu'd Diſcourſe: Which put Sir <hi>George</hi> into ſuch a conſternation, that he ſaid privately to his Fellow-Priſoners, <hi>There is my Buſineſs done.</hi> If there could be any thing plainer then this, let the <hi>Conſideration of the People judge.</hi> For why <hi>Coleman</hi> ſhould be hang'd for the payment of 5000 <hi>l.</hi> upon the Accompt of Treaſon, and Sir <hi>George</hi> be Acquitted for receiving the ſame 5000 <hi>l.</hi> for the ſame Treaſon, is a Riddle worth expounding.</p>
               <p>But to return to the <hi>Epitome,</hi> As for <hi>Corker,</hi> ſays the <hi>Abbreviator, Oates</hi> charg'd him to have ſeen a Patent in his hand to be <hi>Biſhop of London.</hi> (He
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51086:20"/>ſhould have added, that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> alſo heard him ſay, <hi>That he hop'd it would not be long,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ere he ſhould be in the</hi> Exerciſe <hi>of his</hi> Function, which made all the People laugh.) That <hi>Corker,</hi> being Preſident of the <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictine</hi> Monks, did conſent to the Raiſing of Six thouſand Pound, to be contributed by them toward the Deſign. That he heard <hi>Corker</hi> diſlike the choice of <hi>Pickering,</hi> to Kill the King, <hi>becauſe he attended upon the Altar;</hi> and might miſs an opportunity while he was at Maſs. That <hi>Marſhall</hi> knew of <hi>Pickering</hi>'s deſign, and made the ſame <hi>Objection</hi> againſt him; and that he ſaw him at the <hi>Conſult</hi> in <hi>August.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the <hi>Obſervator</hi> is offended, that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> would not be poſitive, when <hi>Marſhall</hi> ask'd him, <hi>What day it was he was at the</hi> Conſult? Yet <hi>Corker</hi> could ſay for himſelf, <hi>That no mortal Man could tell where he was, or what he did and ſaid every day and hour of his whole life.</hi> So that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> muſt be Immortal, or elſe muſt be no Witneſs for the King. But what they urg'd againſt him, made the more for him; For the leſs poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive he was, the more he was to be believ'd, in regard that ſuch a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny could not be tax'd of Malice or Raſhneſs.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Corker,</hi> and <hi>Marſhall</hi> themſelves, the firſt made a Pedantic, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther School Boy-like Declamation, to prove in the firſt place the Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Plot, becauſe ſo many Perſons of Quality were engaged in it: But he might have remember'd, that it was not the Rabble, but the Chiefeſt and moſt Noble among the Senators of <hi>Rome,</hi> that were engaged in the Conſpiracy of <hi>Catiline;</hi> and the chiefeſt Nobility of <hi>France</hi> in the <hi>Guiſian</hi> League, againſt their Sovereign <hi>Henry</hi> III. Bie-and-bie, becauſe he would have two ſtrings to his Bowe, he argues the ſame Improbabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Plot, becauſe it was known to ſo few. So that firſt he wonder'd why ſuch a deſign ſhould be communicated to ſo many, and then he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd ſo few ſhould know it. A Harangue ſo little to the purpoſe, and ſo full of impertinent Extravagancy, as if his Brains has been as inviſible as his pretended Witneſſes. Seeing then the Court would ſwallow none of theſe gilded Pills, he flew at the Evidence, and accus'd them to be, or elſe have been <hi>men of ſcandalous Lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Clodius accuſat Moechos.</q>
               <p>For grant them to be, or have been <hi>men of ſcandalous Lives,</hi> they could never be more ſcandalous then He, who at that time ſtood Impeach'd of Forethought Murder and Treaſon, and whoſe Acquittal has rather confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the guilt of his Crimes, then juſtifi'd his Innocence. But as theſe were things barely ſaid, without any proof in the world, the Kings Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence muſt and will live, to the Reproach of a raſh <hi>miſpriſion Jury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marſhall</hi> told a Story of a <hi>mark in his head behind,</hi> talking as if he had <hi>a knock in his Cradle;</hi> which vaniſhing, upon the Teſtimony of Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Waller,</hi> he made a great ſtir of what Witneſſes he could have had, had he had time; but that Point was clear'd, that he had both leave and time ſufficient, by Captain <hi>Richardſon.</hi> Theſe Cards failing, they both fell upon Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> for not Apprehending them ſooner, Arguing from thence, That if Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had known they had been in the Plot, he would have apprehended them ſooner. But this was all but Suppoſition; ſo that as long as they were apprehended, it was well enough. He was then in a hurry, about apprehending the more conſiderable Inſtruments. He was not to burthen his memory too much, having ſo many to charge; and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51086:20"/>therefore took his time, and was not bound to tell them when they ſhould be apprehended. And though <hi>Marſhall</hi> popping accidentally into a Houſe where a Search was making, affirm'd, <hi>He might have gone away, if he would;</hi> it was ſworn, <hi>That he would have gone away, if he could:</hi> But that Sir <hi>William Waſler</hi> had given <hi>Order,</hi> that any Body might be let in, but that no Body ſhould be let out.</p>
               <p>Then they call'd one <hi>Nell Rigby,</hi> a confident Slut, to teſtifie that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> came a begging to <hi>Pickering</hi> for Charity, and that <hi>Pickering</hi> bid her <hi>ſhut the door</hi> againſt him. A very likely Tale of a Draggle-tail, that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſhould come a begging to <hi>Pickering</hi> for Charity, when <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread</hi> at the ſame time owed him Fourſcore pound, by Bill under his hand, not yet paid. However <hi>Marſhall</hi> made his concluſion, That it was an <hi>improbable</hi> thing, that they ſhould truſt him with ſuch a Plot, and ſuffer him to want; and more then that, ſend him with ſuch a flea in his car, when he might eaſily ſupply himſelf by a diſcovery.</p>
               <p>But this is a wrong Concluſion, as theſe People make uſe of many, upon a wrong ground. For it is abſolutely deny'd, that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was in that neceſſity: So that it is plain Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> came to crave <hi>Pickering</hi>'s Charity for ſome other Perſon. But the ſurly and penurious <hi>Pickering,</hi> not liking thoſe charitable demands, (And that he was a ſurly, cruel, ill-natur'd Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, is manifeſt, from his being pitch'd upon to murther the King) bid the Maid <hi>ſhut the door,</hi> and not let him come again. Of which <hi>Ruffianly</hi> piece of Incivility, Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was wiſer then to take notice, or give them occaſion to think he was ſo weak, as by an unſeaſonable diſcovery, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge himſelf upon an inſignificant <hi>Butcherly</hi> Monk.</p>
               <p>And beſides, they had ſuch a ſlight opinion of his weak parts, or rather ſuch a confidence in the greatneſs of their own, that they ſcorn'd all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries; and perhaps they might have had reaſon enough to have thought ſo, had they not by that ſilly and impolitic Murther of Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund-Bury Godfrey,</hi> rather pour'd oyl then water upon the Fire, and ſed that into a blazing Flame, which elſe they might have eaſily quench'd, and puſt away the Smoke.</p>
               <p>At laſt <hi>Corker</hi> call'd for two <hi>Gillian a Croydens,</hi> that lay in <hi>Perdue</hi> in or about the Court, ready prepar'd to prove, that <hi>Stapleton,</hi> and not <hi>Corker,</hi> had been for many Years Preſident of the <hi>Benedictine Monks.</hi> To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe being demanded by the Chief Juſtice, a general Queſtion, Who was Preſident of the <hi>Benedictine Monks?</hi> They anſwer'd as generally, Mr. <hi>Stapleton;</hi> which was taken for granted, without further Inquiry: though <hi>Corker</hi> gave him a fair hint, by ſaying, <hi>He was at</hi> Paris <hi>with</hi> Stapleton, <hi>and therefore could not officiate in his ſtead.</hi> Upon this Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> was call'd again, but never examin'd: why it was not done, he muſt be a <hi>Solomon</hi> that gives the Reaſon, unleſs it were for fear he ſhould clear the Point.</p>
               <p>After all, when nothing but Deſpair hover'd before their Eyes, <hi>Marſhall</hi> began, as the <hi>Epitomizer</hi> ſaith, a Harangue ſo <hi>pathetical, weighty,</hi> and <hi>moving;</hi> but as the Court ſaid, ſo fawning, ſo invective, ſo fallacious, ſo affrontive to the Court, ſo far from Self-defence, which was the Text he was to follow, that he was commanded to leave Sermonizing to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as abounding in his Rhetorical Flowers, that had nothing but the ill ſcent of the <hi>French</hi> Marigold.</p>
               <p>At length the Lord Chief Juſtice told them plainly, <hi>That their Defence had been very mean, and that their Cauſe look'd much better, before they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51086:21"/>had ſpoken a word for themſelves.</hi> Which the Jury ought to have taken more notice of, than of <hi>Marſhall</hi>'s gingling expreſſions. But certainly ſome gentle <hi>Conſtellation</hi> reign'd that day, more tender-hearted than the weeping <hi>Pleiades;</hi> Or elſe Mercy and Compaſſion themſelves had ſome particular pique againſt Truth, and were reſolved to put an Affront upon her. Or elſe <hi>Laſſa Crudelitas</hi> began to grow penitent, and cry <hi>Peccavi</hi> for her former Severity, which (and for which, we may thank a wiſe Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) will certainly be the conſtruction of them that ſhall hereafter go to play the <hi>Cauſinus</hi>'s with our Story: Which, however, the Conſideration of the People may prevent, by giving a more juſt and ſolid Verdict.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51086:21"/>
            <head>THE ADDRESS TO ALL Perſons of Reaſon, and Lovers OF THE Proteſtant Religion, Of what Rank ſoever they be.</head>
            <p>HAving thus (my <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen</hi>) giv'n you this exact and ſhort Account of the ſeveral Abſurdities, Falſities, Falſe Abbreviations, Falſe Concluſions, Impertinent and Senſleſs Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and Fawning Inſinuations, with which the <hi>Writer</hi> of a certain Inſamous and Rebellious <hi>Libel,</hi> has made all the Reflections his Rancour and Malice could invent upon the late <hi>Judicial Proceedings,</hi> as being the Vehicles which he thought moſt proper to convey his intended Poyſon into the veins of the Nation: I know not whether you are more ſurpriz'd, for ſurpriz'd I am ſure you muſt be, at the Irreligion of an <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del,</hi> defending Acts of Impiety; or the <hi>Confidence</hi> of a <hi>Subject,</hi> contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the Juſtice of his Sovereign. For let his Pretences be what they will, his deſign is this, and onely this, to annihilate the Plot, and by that means to full the Vigilancy of the Kingdom aſleep, that they may the more ſecurely make up the late Breach, and begin again with their work.</p>
            <p>To effect this, Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> poor Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Iſſachar</hi> of all their Scandals and Reproaches; He muſt be preſt to Death, (not for ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mute in Court, I'm ſure) the <hi>pitiful Wretch,</hi> as the <hi>Abbreviator</hi> calls him, ſo contemn'd and deſpis'd by the <hi>Benedictine Rabbies,</hi> and <hi>Flaunty Taunty Jeſuites,</hi> muſt be trod upon, and dye the death of a Worm; and all, becauſe he outwitted their Cunning. The moſt convincing Argument of his Integrity, that ſuch <hi>Goliahs,</hi> as they, fell by his Imbecillity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:51086:22"/>Nay further, <hi>my Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> you have ſome reaſon to give this <hi>Compendium Scribler</hi> your humble thanks, for having ſuch mean and Hender thoughts of you too, to be ſo ſure of your being ſurpriz'd at the <hi>Incoherenees and Impoſſibilities</hi> of a Charge, which the <hi>Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England,</hi> and conſequently <hi>many of your ſelves,</hi> voted to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial and true; and at the <hi>weight of Defences,</hi> adjudg'd to be ſo weak and unſcholar-like by all the ſelect Judges of the Nation.</p>
            <p>But when you conſider how it has been the practice of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abſolutely to deny, or extenuate their perpetrated Crimes. So <hi>Cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rela</hi> in the Life of <hi>Sixtus</hi> V. labors to extenuate the Murther of <hi>Henry</hi> III. ſaying. <hi>That</hi> Jacob Clement <hi>committed the Fact, meerly by the impulſe of his own Zeal, and that there was no Subornation of others that enrag'd him to the Act.</hi> When the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> themſelves were they that fetch't him, <hi>a poor Criminal Dominican,</hi> out of the Cloyſter where he lay Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd for ſeveral Rogueries; and never left, till they had Charm'd him to compleat the number of his Villanies, by the Murther of his Prince: As may be ſeen more at large, in <hi>Hoſpinian</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtory of the Jeſuites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Mezecay,</hi> the great Hiſtorian himſelf confeſſes, that the <hi>Ruffian</hi> acknowledg'd to the Count of <hi>Brienne,</hi> then in the Baſtile, that he had inſtructions and directions from others, and a counterfeit Letter of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the name of the Preſident <hi>Harlay,</hi> to facilitate his Acceſs.</p>
            <p>When you conſider that it has been all along the longing deſire of the <hi>Triple-Crown'd Squire</hi> to regain <hi>England;</hi> And how zealous Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> was, to promote the <hi>Spamſh Invaſion;</hi> And how he ammated <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> to the Fatal Deſtruction of his Expenſive <hi>Armada;</hi> And how probable it is, that thoſe vehement Thirſtings and Yawnings after the Fertile Glebes of theſe Fortunate Iſlands, ſtill remain with the working Wits at <hi>Rome,</hi> one effect whereof, beſides ſeveral others, was their curſed <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, when you conſider theſe things, and how improbable it is that Men of their Principles, ſhould leave off their old Cuſtoms; I am apt to ſuppoſe, that you will not ſo eaſily jump with the <hi>Compendium-monger</hi> in his Opinion. That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Diſcovery is ſo <hi>monſtrous,</hi> or of ſuch <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing parts,</hi> as to ſhew it ſelf ſo <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>chimerical,</hi> as this <hi>Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing were at last reduced to proportion,</hi> as he moſt <hi>Jeſuitically</hi> inſinuates, <hi>it was done by the efforts and skill of better Artiſts.</hi> Rather he ought to be call'd to an Account, whom he means by <hi>better Artiſts.</hi> For the <hi>Lords of the Council,</hi> the <hi>Lords aſſembled in Parliament,</hi> and the whole <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> had the <hi>Examination</hi> of all things. The <hi>Attorney</hi> and <hi>Sollicitor General,</hi> and all the <hi>King's Council,</hi> had alſo their Inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into the Proofs; ſo then theſe muſt be the <hi>better Artiſts</hi> which he means, that aſſiſted Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in the management of his Defects. It lies heavy upon the <hi>Two Committees of Secreſie,</hi> and nothing but <hi>a Jeſuites weighty Defence</hi> can help 'em out. They were very <hi>ill Artiſts</hi> (though our <hi>Obſervator</hi> be ſo courteous as to grant 'em <hi>better</hi> then Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>) that all their private Debates and Conſultations, ſhould be only to produce a Plot for Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s ſake, that ſhould ſo eaſily be render'd Defective and Fabulous, by a <hi>Compendium-mongers untainted Witneſſes.</hi> Not ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted</hi> neither, as he dreams, nor ſo much <hi>Maſters of Reputation,</hi> either by <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in regard they have been all ſo notoriouſly and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably diſprov'd; And that it has been ſo fairly made out, that they onely came to lend their Friends a ſtretch of Equivocation, if it would have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51086:22"/>ſerv'd their turn. Neither do I believe this <hi>Plot-Plaiſterer</hi> to be a Man of that Grandeur, to authorize him to revile any Man with the term of <hi>Profligated Wretch,</hi> unleſs it be, becauſe he may be Excommunicated by <hi>Don Paolo d'Oliva;</hi> nor to be ſo good a <hi>Phyſiognomist,</hi> as to judge by any Mans <hi>Temper</hi> or <hi>Poverty,</hi> of his Inclinations; And therefore he might have ſpar'd his <hi>Bear-Garden Arguments,</hi> when he wrote to <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the <hi>Obſervator</hi> believe, that the weight of his Defences lies in <hi>Ifs</hi> and <hi>Ands,</hi> and <hi>How can it be poſſible?</hi> Then we leave it to the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the People, upon what has been already ſaid; but if he think that the Ponderoſity lies in their Vows, Denials, and Proteſtations, he only builds in the Air, and muſt have Dr. <hi>Wilkinſon</hi>'s <hi>Engine,</hi> to keep it from falling. For it is certain that the Pope does aſſume to himſelf an abſolute power to excommunicate Kings. <hi>Sixtus</hi> V. Excommunicated two him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Henry de Navarre, Henry Valois</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Now let us ſee what the Subſtance and Penalties of this Excommunication are.</p>
            <p>The Pope order'd the King to be Excommunicated, which was, ſaith <hi>Cicarela,</hi> in the Life of the ſame Pope; That he ſhould be ſtruck with the Thunder of <hi>Anathema;</hi> That he ſhould incur all Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, which are contain'd in the Sacred Canons, in the general and particular Conſtitutions, and the <hi>Bull of the Lords Supper.</hi> And the ſame Cenſure ſhall be good againſt all that aſſiſt the ſame King, either with Counſel, or any way elſe.</p>
            <p>And by his Excommunication thunder'd out againſt <hi>Henry de Navarre,</hi> and <hi>Henry de Bourbon,</hi> Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> he declar'd them <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and uncapable of ſucceeding to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> He alſo abſolv'd their Subjects from all Oaths of Allegiance and Fidelity ſworn to thoſe Princes.</p>
            <p>Now if CHARLES II. King of <hi>England,</hi> be Excommunicated at <hi>Rome,</hi> as there is no queſtion to be made, but He is; for any <hi>Papist</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf a Subject to CHARLES II. King of <hi>England,</hi> being Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, is not only to diſobey the Pope, but to contemn and render invalid the Thunder of <hi>Anathema,</hi> the Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure, the general and particular Conſtitutions, and the <hi>Bull of the Lords Supper,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to renounce his Religion. And therefore all their Denials, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations and Imprecations ſignifi'd nothing, becauſe they had relation to no Body; For according to the tenor of their Excommunication, an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated King is no Body, a meer Statue of a King: And therefore for them to profeſs themſelves Jeſuites and Prieſts, and pray for the King, was Non-ſenſe; and they dy'd both like Fools and Knaves together, in regard it was impoſſible for the King to be any thing to them that were true Subjects to the Pope.</p>
            <p>Now that the King ſtands Eternally Excommunicated at <hi>Rome,</hi> as an <hi>Heretick,</hi> is not only plain from the Expreſſions of <hi>Coleman,</hi> but is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, from this, That no Man of true Religion or Piety, I may add Morality, would dare to invade the Dominions of a Sovereign Prince, call himſelf His Subject, and violate His Laws, if he thought either His Laws to be Laws, or Him to be a King.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Argument holds againſt the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s <hi>untainted Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> who might eaſily ſay any thing, when they were taught, and believ'd that what they ſaid, was neither in a Court of Judicature, nor before them that were Magiſtrates. For the Magiſtrates of a depos'd King can be no
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51086:23"/>Magiſtrates, according to the true Papiſtical Doctrine. And indeed it was the Devils Maſter-piece, when he had invented a Pope, to entail thoſe two Powers of <hi>Excommunication</hi> and <hi>Abſolution</hi> to his Chair; which are the Foundation of all breach of Oaths, all Proteſtations, Vows and Impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; of all Infidelity, and Chriſtian Irregularity.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Langhorne</hi>'s averring, <hi>That he did not believe the Pope had any Authority to Excommunicate, and conſequently to Depoſe the King;</hi> in ſo doing, he deni'd the Doctrine of the chiefeſt Fathers of his Profeſſion, <hi>Petrus Ribadeneira, Becanas</hi> of <hi>Mentz, Jacobus Simmancha</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>os, Bellarmine</hi> himſelf, <hi>Hoſius</hi> the Cardinal, and <hi>Molanus,</hi> who all unanimouſly teach the ſame Doctrine, <hi>That the Pope has Authority to Depoſe and Excommunicate Heretick Kings and Princes, and to Abſolve their Subjects from their Allegiance and Obedience to them.</hi> So that he muſt either have ſome ſtrange Reſerve to himſelf, for that he did not ſpeak, but only deliver his equivocating Conceptions in writing, or elſe he could be no Papiſt, but muſt dye the Lord knows what, a double Traytor to the Pope, and to his Prince; No Man can ſerve two Maſters: And therefore he did but imitate St. <hi>Peter</hi> in a wrong ſenſe, as if he thought to have got the name of an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> by denying his Maſter <hi>Antichrist</hi> thrice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Cock crow'd once. And thus we behold the Policy of Papiſts, who, when they deal with others, always propoſe to them the Pretence and Proteſtations of Religion, and the Arguments of their Chriſtian Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, while under the pretext of theſe, they hide their <hi>Self-policy,</hi> to uſe it in time and place convenient; which no Body can for the preſent diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, nor know the depth of the Intrigue, but themſelves.</p>
            <p>But now, as if he were the Supreme Chieſtain of the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> he undertakes, like another <hi>Guido Vaux,</hi> with his <hi>dark Lanthorn,</hi> to pry into Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Converſation,</hi> and to <hi>blow up</hi> his Repute with a <hi>Gunpowder-Plot of Recrimination.</hi> But all this while, who is this <hi>Bull of Baſin,</hi> that bellows out all theſe <hi>Reproaches</hi> againſt the Evidence for the King and Kingdom? Common Fame <hi>(my Lords and Gentlemen)</hi> ſpeaks him a Priſoner, and one that has ſo long continued. So then for one Beggar, for if he be not ſo, he muſt be a Knave, to reproach another ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him, if Poverty be the Crime, the more Contemptible. But let him be a <hi>Croeſus,</hi> he is a Papiſt by his own acknowledgment, and conſequently a Party; a Party that by the malice and embitterment of his kicking and wincing Expreſſions, ſhews himſelf to be in the number of the <hi>Gall'd Horſes,</hi> that have been ſo ſeverely rub'd by a clear and undoubted Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. He is the Profeſſor of a Religion which is a ſcandal to all <hi>Europe;</hi> a Religion <hi>Marforio'd</hi> and <hi>Paſquin'd</hi> by the frequent Satyrs of thoſe that behold the daily Fooleries of its moſt exalted <hi>Aarons</hi> and <hi>High Prieſts;</hi> a Religion that maintains that inveterate Hatred and inbred Antipathy to <hi>Proteſtantiſm,</hi> contrary to the character of all Chriſtian Piety, that it has no thought of Reconciliation, or Humane Charity for it; which to make out gradually, we ſhall thus begin, and make uſe of none but thoſe of their own Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Hear in the firſt place <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> thundering out thoſe diſmal Sarcaſms againſt the Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtracy of his own Religion, <hi>cap.</hi> 61. de van. ſcion. <hi>But the ancient Conſtitutions of the Fathers falling from their Majeſty, and later Pontifical Priviledges prevailing through dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Cuſtom, ſuch Popes and Apoſtles aſcend the Chair of Christ, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly there ſate Scribes and Phariſees in the Chair of</hi> Moſes, <hi>who only
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51086:23"/>ſay, and do nothing, impoſing heavy burthens upon the ſhoulders of the People. They are Hypocrites, doing all their works, making ſhews of their Religion in Scenes. They ſhut the gate of Heaven, and will neither enter themſelves, nor let others go in. The Pope of</hi> Rome <hi>himſelf is a moſt heavy and intolerable to all, whoſe Pomp and Pride never any Tyrant equall'd, They boast that the ſtate of Religion and the Church conſiſts in them alone, throwing the Religious Functions upon others, and in the mean time buſied in making Laws for their own ſupport, receiving the Profits of the Church, themſelves both lazy and flagitious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he gives you a Catalogue of thoſe Reverend Fathers of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII. of whom <hi>Platina</hi> ſays, <hi>That he was ſo ambitious of the Pontificate,</hi> ut nil Ambitione &amp; Fraude praetermiſerit, quod ad eam rem conſequendam pertinere arbitraretur, <hi>he omitted nothing that Ambition or Fraud could prompt him to, to attain his ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After him <hi>Paulus, Sixtus, Alexander, Julius,</hi> the moſt famous diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Chriſtian world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eugenius</hi> IV. who caus'd <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>adiſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> to break his Faith with the <hi>Turk,</hi> to the loſs of his own life, and the irreparable damage of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> VI. that poyſon'd <hi>Zizim,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> Brother, to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick detriment of <hi>Europe.</hi> To whom we may add again, <hi>Alexander</hi> VI. ſporting and dallying in public with his Curteſan <hi>Vannoccia,</hi> and filling all <hi>Rome</hi> with his Baſtards, and giving himſelf up to the Devil, to enrich his impious Son <hi>Caeſar Borgia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent</hi> X. committing Inceſt with his Siſter-in-law <hi>Donna Olympia,</hi> and reſigning St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair to a Harlot.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, the preſent <hi>Odeſchalchi,</hi> not a little Famous for his impotent Amours with the Princeſs of <hi>Roſſana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Agricola,</hi> when he comes to pour out the Vial of his juſt indignation upon the Rabble rout of Prieſts and Fryars: <hi>In this See,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>with the vaſter</hi> Leviathans <hi>and</hi> Behemoth, <hi>ſwims the leſſer Fry of Money mumpers, Clapperdogeons, Beggars with great Beards, girt about with Ropes and Halters, Wallet-bearers with wooden Shooes, or ſometimes bare-foot, ſometimes in black, ſometimes in gray, then in white, Benedictines, Beruardines, Auguſtines, Franciſcans,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Men whoſe Lives are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally moſt infamous for their Covetouſneſs, Lust, Pride, Gluttony, Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all manner of Iniquity:</hi> Which is a very fair Character from ſo great a Man of his own Religion, and the Eccleſiaſtical Government of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now come to the <hi>Nipotiſm</hi> and <hi>Putaniſm</hi> of the Romiſh <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the Holy City. In the firſt of which, the Author of the ſame Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, complains, <hi>That all Chriſtendom is ſcandaliz'd; that they who make ſo great a Profeſſion of a Religion, ſhould ſo little believe it.</hi> Nay, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rome</hi> themſelves have a Proverb among them, <hi>That the Emperors firſt taught Tyranny, and the Popes practiſe it.</hi> And a <hi>German Prelate</hi> lately living, was wont to ſay, <hi>That the Popes Kinred acquire this world by their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles Indulgence, and that their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncles loſe the other world by their Nephews Vices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> made ſuch a good uſe of the Popes Authority, that whenever he was upon any miſchievous deſign, he would ſay, <hi>That he very well knew that what he went about was juſt, becauſe his Father had the Holy Ghost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:51086:24"/>
               <hi>It is not unknown,</hi> ſaith another, <hi>to every Scullion in</hi> Rome. <hi>how odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous the Nipotiſm is to Heaven, Earth, Nobles, Plebeians, all Ranks and Qualities of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author <hi>of the Whoredom of</hi> Rome, having aſſembled all the kind Ladies and Curteſans of the City to elect a new Pope: Some are for this Cardinal, and others for another; ſome they chuſe, and ſome they reject. Thoſe that they vote for, are ſuch, whoſe kindneſs to women they have experimented. Thoſe that they reject, are the Devils of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> that have little or no affection for the Female Sex. A moſt bleſſed <hi>Vicar of Christ,</hi> to expoſe St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, himſelf, and all the great <hi>Nimrods</hi> of his Church and Society, to the merited Reproaches of every Satyrical Pen.</p>
            <p>But this is not all; the Author of <hi>La Doppia impiccata,</hi> printed at <hi>Orbitello,</hi> under the Noſe of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> brings Madam <hi>Pecunia,</hi> and arraigns her at the Bar of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> for ſeveral and weighty Crimes; where being ask'd, <hi>How ſhe behav'd her ſelf among her Neighbors?</hi> She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes, how ſhe feduc'd the Holy Jeſuite <hi>Columbera.</hi> For he, good Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous to get a little money by his labors, was wont to ſteal out of the window of his Cell by the help of a Rope, and in his venerable Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, to go with his Breviary and his Lanthorn in his hand, having underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to debauch a young Virgin, between whoſe breaſts, it was not long before he gain'd the honor for his Patron, Father (<hi>ypriano,</hi> to preach with all his amorous Eloquence. So that of an <hi>Apoſtolick Miſſionary,</hi> he ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealy became the braveſt Doctor in the Pulpit of the Fleſh, that ever diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of the Beatifical Viſion of ſnowy Boſoms, and the contemplation of that heav'n, where he had ſo often lay'n in the ſwooning Raptures of his Luſt. After that, he makes a bloody Complaint againſt the poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for faſtening ſo many infamous Sodomies among the Prelates and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they have made a very <hi>Pentapolis</hi> of the Holy See: wherein ſuch is the value of that infernal Merchandize, that the excrement of a Page is at twelve Crowns an Ounce.</p>
            <p>Being ask'd, <hi>What Frauds ſhe had committed?</hi> She anſwer'd, ſhe had caus'd the Abbot <hi>Dini</hi> to counterfeit <hi>an Order of the Chamber of the Magazines in</hi> Venice, to let go two Galeots ſent by the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> to that Republick, and all for 2000 Duckers; and hath alſo caus'd the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Maſcambruno,</hi> to alter the ſenſe of the <hi>Canon</hi> in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Briefs,</hi> to ſatiate the <hi>Vatican Harpie</hi> with double Crowns.</p>
            <p>Being ask'd, <hi>What occaſion of Offences ſhe had given, in reference to ſcandalous Actions?</hi> Alas! they were without number, ſhe ſaid. Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſhe had been the Occaſion, that <hi>Innocent</hi> X. would not give Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the <hi>Portugal</hi> Ambaſſador, about the Affairs and Intereſt of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in that Kingdom, till he had given <hi>Donna Olympia</hi> ſuch a number of Duckers.</p>
            <p>And that Father <hi>Caravita</hi> the Jeſuite, being in poſſeſſion of the Oratory of the <hi>Bacchettoni,</hi> had ſo often adjuſted his Pardons to the quantity of the Sum agreed; while he caus'd the poor Husbands to be contented with the Horns that were planted upon their heads, and made them believe, to that purpoſe, with his Cabaliſtic Eloquence, that it was a meritorious thing to wear Brow. Antlers for the love of God. The Purſe of <hi>Pompeo Giuſtinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> one of the wry-necks of the ſame Society, knew his tricks well enough; who, after he had with great expence enjoy'd a Mercers wife, was by him condemn'd to give ſix Silver Candleſticks to the Oratory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:51086:24"/>'Twas ſhe that had been the Occaſion of the ſcandalous. Amours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Cardinal <hi>Azzolino,</hi> and his Cardinaleſs the Queen of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Twas ſhe that perſwaded the <hi>Bolognan</hi> Abbeſs to betray into the hands of Cardinal <hi>Antenio</hi> one of her choiceſt and moſt beautiful Virgins.</p>
            <p>'Twas ſhe that caus'd <hi>Donna Olympia</hi> to ſend for the <hi>Thaes,</hi> that her Nephew <hi>Cadinal Maldachino,</hi> had been with the night before, and made her reſtore the 200 Duckers, which he had given her for his pleaſure; and ſo diſappointed the poor Slur of a hundred Gewgaws.</p>
            <p>'Twas ſhe that caus'd Monſignior <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Beneventum,</hi> to aſſiſt with his Pontificial habits at the digging up a certain Treaſure, to conjure away the Devil, as if he had deſign'd in his Miter and Rocket to ſing Maſs with the Inhabitants of Hell.</p>
            <p>Being ask'd whether ſhe had ever been guilty of abuſing the Male ſex? ſhe anſwered, ſhe was a woman, but referr'd her ſelf to the Schools of the Jeſuits, the moſt learned <hi>Lyceum's,</hi> where that Art was taught; thoſe tilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing places, where they run at the Ring with ſo much bravery and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; the Maſters of thoſe Chairs delighting in moſt difficult Attempts, as having now forſaken the poverty of Religion, and applying themſelves to more expenſive luxuries, becoming Grandeur, and the Management of Secular Affairs. There would be no end of the Diſcoveries of the Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of this Religion, were that, the ſole buſineſs of theſe ſheets. However, this may ſuffice to ſhew out of the mouths of the Papiſts themſelves, that <hi>Rome</hi> is only a Den of Thieves and Robbers, that their Monaſteries are but Sties of Ignorance and uncleanneſs, and their Nunneries meer <hi>Hollands Leagures:</hi> Thus much then for their Eccleſiaſtical Government; now for their Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They teach, that all Pacts, Conſtitutions, Agreements of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings and Princes, not confirmed by the Pope, are void, and of no Effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Simancha,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Badoxos</hi> teaches, <hi>That there is no Faith to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved with Hereticks, though after Oath given.</hi> And in another place, <hi>That there can be no Peace or Commerce with them, and therefore no Faith can be obſerved toward them, though confirmed by Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conradus Brunus</hi> confirmeth this, averring. <hi>That there can be no Peace between a Catholick and a Heretick; and that it is a wicked and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Condition of a Treaty, that allows to Hereticks the Exerciſe of their Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin Becanus</hi> teaches. <hi>That Liberty of Religion granted to a</hi> Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran <hi>or</hi> Calviniſt, <hi>s altogether unlawful, and repugnant to the Law of God, and only to be permitted no longer than needs muſt, to avoid a greater Miſchief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They teach, <hi>That it is the duty of the Roman Catholicks to deſtroy and root out the Proteſtants by fire, poiſon, ſword, gunpowder, or any other way moſt opportune and convenient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To confirm this, ſaith Cardinal <hi>Baronius, The Office of St.</hi> Peter <hi>is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; to feed and kill; feed my ſheep; kill and eat: by which Text Saint</hi> Peter <hi>is commanded to kill and ſlay as well as keep and feed. It remains them, Holy Father, that you draw the ſword of St.</hi> Peter <hi>againſt the wicked He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, as being constituted by God over King, and Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That Kings and Princes may be poyſon'd, or otherwiſe taken away by their Subjects, being Roman Catholicks, if their Divines do once ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them excommunicate.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:51086:25"/>5. That Heretical Magiſtrates and Princes are to be accounted excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, if not <hi>de facto,</hi> yet <hi>de Jure,</hi> and conſequently may be lawfully aſſaſſinated by their Subjects.</p>
            <p>This is the Doctrine of <hi>Mariana, Petrus de Onna, Simmancha, Creſwell, Treſham:</hi> And <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the ſecond decreed, that they ſhould not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Murtherers, that kill'd any of the Enemies of the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church.</p>
            <p>As for the Doctrine of <hi>Equivocation,</hi> ſo publickly taught, and ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently practiſed by them, there has been occaſion to ſpeak ſo much alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy through the Nation, that it will be needleſs to repeat any more. I will only add, that all thoſe proteſtations and pawnings of their ſalvation were only Bugbears, with which they thought to ſcare and amuſe the ears of the Proteſtants, till they had ſtifled all farther Diſcovery. But now they find, they were ſo far from being innocent of the Murther of Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund—Godfrey,</hi> that they rather choſe to murther themſelves, than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the foulneſs of their Crimes. Thus then it appears that in the Popiſh Religion there is neither Honeſty nor Credit; a Religion broach'd and maintain'd only by the worldly Policy of a company of Lordanes, to rob and defraud all mankind; a Religion that borrows it's Devotion from the Silver-Smith, and whoſe brighteſt Luminaries are the Wax-Chandlers Tapers. And ſhall the Profeſſor of ſuch a Religion as this, my Lords and Gentlemen, perſwade the Profeſſors of the noble, candid and magnanimous Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon which never any of theſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations could be thrown by the worſt of her Enemies, that he is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon fit to charm ye out of your ſenſes with his <hi>Ifs</hi> and his <hi>Ands;</hi> his <hi>How can this be poſſibles?</hi> and <hi>How can ye imagins?</hi> when there is not the leaſt improbabilitie in the deepeſt of his Objections? Will ye not rather number him with thoſe that ſo vainly vindicated the <hi>Powder-Plot,</hi> the Maſſacre of <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Guiſian</hi> League, and the murther of two Kings of <hi>France,</hi> by his wretched attempt to evade the murther of your follow ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the foul Treaſon acted againſt your Prince? Or can you have better thoughts of him, but that he is one that ſtrives, as they did, to Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fianize the Crimes of his Aſſociates, that he may hinder the progreſs of your Proſecution? Does he tell ye who committed thoſe Crimes? No—but he fells ye, he hopes ye will find them out at length—and would throw the charge upon <hi>sticklers</hi> againſt <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>King-haters;</hi> as if any had proved themſelves more buſie in thoſe things then his own gang. We know there are ſticklers, and perhaps thoſe that are no great friends to the King: But 'tis the humour of our Engliſh Male-contents, unleſs of thoſe that are refin'd with St. <hi>Omers</hi> Education, rather openly to ruffle with their Prince, then to contrive ſecret Aſſaſſinations and Treaſons. Shall he come with an old quaſh'd Endictment from a Pie-powder Court (for ſuch a one I may call it in reſpect of thoſe High Courts where Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in reference to the late proceedings) to vilifie the Kings Evidence, ſo fairly venturing Life and Reputation for the preſervation of his King and Country? What a noiſe doth the <hi>Fool</hi> make with the <hi>Women</hi> of <hi>Haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?</hi> Truly the <hi>women</hi> of <hi>Haſtings</hi> were the moſt unkind women that ever I heard of. The Miniſter of the Pariſh would have prevented a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical Innovation</hi> upon their bearing-places, and they would needs whip him form. Certainly thoſe women were very popiſhly affected, or elſe they would never have had the laſh ſo ready at their fingers ends. And the Magiſtrates of <hi>Haſtings</hi> were vehemently to be ſuſpected, that they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51086:25"/>did not either find the man guilty, or elſe ſend the women to the ſcourging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt, for mutinying ſo furiouſly againſt the Aſſertor of their lawful privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. To ſee the difference of Opinions! Had he been a <hi>Cardinal</hi> that had been accus'd, I warrant ye, the men of <hi>Haſtings</hi> would have found him guilty, and the <hi>Compendium monger</hi> would have made no more words on't. Now what an Act has this <hi>Compendium-ſcribler</hi> done, to juſtifie an illegal uproar of miſ intelligenc'd Baggages, to vilifie an Evidence, that had he had a grain of Allegiance, ſhould have been more ſacred to him? Now, the truth is, the Endictment was true, but a pack of knaves and fools, leaning for favour and affection, and ſome products thereof, did very ſcandalouſly take the Criminals part againſt their Miniſter. And that this is true, you have the Attorney General's word for it, who having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken cognizance of the matter, declar'd in open Court, that <hi>there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it.</hi> All which the Obſervator moſt ingeniouſly leaves our, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the double Uſance of Popery. But to ſhew how little Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> is afraid of this <hi>Bevis of Southhampton</hi> for the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> he fairly appeals to <hi>Haſtings, Bobbing,</hi> or any other place, where he has officiated in the Countries of <hi>Kent,</hi> or <hi>Suſſex,</hi> to tax him with the leaſt miſdemeanour misbecoming his function, during his abode among them, to which when the Obſervator makes his rejoynder, he ſhall have another ſort of anſwer.</p>
            <p>In the next place, he tells ye a ſtrange tale of <hi>Sir Denny Aſhburnham,</hi> what he ſaid in prejudice of Mr. <hi>Oates.</hi> Truly it was a ſtrange ſtory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. It was a ſpeech might have become a plain Countrey Judice in the Wild of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> but - at a <hi>London</hi> Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer and Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>— to talk as if he had been at a Chriſtening—I wonder he did not bring his Widwife along with him to help him out with ſuch a piece of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipry. Well! You long to know what it was: It was this; <hi>I knew Mr.</hi> Oates <hi>from his Cradle, and when he was a Child,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ireland</hi>'s Tryal, <hi>Pag.</hi> 65.</note> 
               <hi>he was not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that Credit, that we could depend upon what he ſaid.</hi> You ſee what a teſtimony Sugar-plums and Naples-bisket will produce. Did this become a perſon that was ſuch an early Judge of Credit, and conſequently ſhould have had more wit, to bring his Fimtlam ſtories of the ſquabbles of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to invalidate the full grown Evidence of the King in a Concern or ſo high a nature? And to aggravare the folly he had committed, by declaring, that had the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> been only upon Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s ſingle teſtimony, he ſhould have had ſome little doubt of it upon the knowledge of him in his youth. Well, Mr. <hi>Obſervator, Mitch ke ditch ye with</hi> Sir Denny Aſhburn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams<hi>'s Gingerbread-teſtimony.</hi> For there's many an unhappy child makes a good man; ſo that Sir <hi>Denny Aſhburnham</hi>'s kindneſs to the Priſoners, was a little too much antedated. He ſhould have told the Court what he knew Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> to be when he was a man, and not have done like a <hi>Moor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi>'s <hi>Trithemius,</hi> to conjure up the peccadillo's of his childhood, to have appear'd againſt him at ſuch an unſeaſonable time. However, theſe are the two grand accuſations againſt Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> that muſt ſend him to <hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> for perjury. Poor man of Obſervation, they were the beſt he could get, or elſe, we find his virulency to be ſuch, that he would not have ſpar'd him an Inch. An unfortunate Copy of an Endictment from <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings!</hi> which had the Obſervator penurioufly preſerv'd for the lighting his Pipe, would have done him much more good, as not having brought the leaſt tittle of advantage to his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>For my <hi>Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> I ſuppoſe you cannot but believe the King's <hi>Attorney</hi> had much more judgment then this Student <hi>de Collegio
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51086:26"/>Ambubajarum &amp; Balatronum,</hi> and underſtood far better then he, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Indictment. But it is not his bawling and ſcolding, and railing, that muſt do the great work he has undertaken; nay, though he had all his Croneys, the Women of <hi>Haſtings</hi> to help him, he would never ſucceed. For it is ſufficiently known, that the Priſoners at the Bar had all the fair play in the world; they had both time and liberty to call their Witneſſes; and when they made their <hi>Objections,</hi> their Witneſſes were heard with all the patience imaginable.</p>
            <p>Their St. <hi>Omers</hi> Youngſters were heard, and re-heard, to their own, and the ſhame of them that ſent 'em.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> Teſtimony not only confronted and baffl'd, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected after wards to be a meer <hi>Jeſuitical Subornation.</hi> Yet theſe contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of their Friends at liberty, they thought would have proved as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> as their Maſter the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after all this apparent Evidence for the King, and no <hi>Diſproofs</hi> againſt them, but only theſe two pieces of <hi>Forgery,</hi> and ſome <hi>few Surmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Suppoſitions,</hi> that ſignin'd nothing either in <hi>Law or Reaſon,</hi> for one ſingle perſon to upbraid the <hi>Juſtice of the whole Nation,</hi> as if the Judges had not already anſwer'd all the <hi>obſolete Obſervations and Deſcants</hi> which the <hi>Compendium</hi> makes, as if they were not able to judge whether Men be perjur'd or no; or as if you your ſelves, who have many of you had the <hi>full Examination</hi> of theſe matters, were to be rebuk'd, and re advis'd to <hi>reform</hi> your judgments, by a <hi>ſcurrilous Rapſody of Slander and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Sir <hi>Denny Aſhburnham,</hi> though he made <hi>a Childiſh Obſervation</hi> upon Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Childhood,</hi> yet he declar'd, <hi>That he found ſo many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances confirming Mr.</hi> Oates<hi>'s Teſtimony,</hi> (as idle as he thought it) <hi>that he was convinc'd of the reality of the thing it ſelf.</hi> Which the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomizer</hi> did well to leave out, becauſe he was one of his own Witneſſes. By which you may ſee what a Worſhipful Knight he was, to come into Court to put a ſlur upon the King's Evidence, when in his Conſcience he thought he ſpoke Truth. And by this you may find, what fair Play the <hi>Obſervator</hi> ſhews you, to make uſe <hi>of pieces of Teſtimony,</hi> meerly ſo far as they make for his own turn.</p>
            <p>After this, he brings two diminutive Dwarfs to ſecond his two <hi>Goliahs,</hi> pretending, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Oates <hi>had accus'd old</hi> Parker, <hi>the Father, of ſpeaking ſcandalous words against the Lords of the Council, notwithſtanding which he was diſinist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer whereto, let him know. That Mr. <hi>Cates</hi> ſtill appeals to the ſame Order, and is ready to make good his Charge. Mr. <hi>Obſervator,</hi> adviſe your Client to <hi>ſleep in a whole skin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>from whence he infers, <hi>That it was no wonder that ſuch a Witneſs ſhould ſwear that Mr.</hi> Preſton <hi>was a Priest, and his Confeſſor; when as the poor Gentleman has not only a Wife, but has liv'd with her for many years.</hi> A moſt profound Argument indeed. And why may not he be allow'd to marry, as well as Cardinal <hi>Maldachini</hi> be allow'd to be dreſs'd in Womens Apparel in a Common Bawdy-houſe? Or <hi>Treſham</hi> the Jeſuite to have either a Doxy, or a Wife; ſuch an one, as upon his Death-Bed compell'd him to damn himſelf, by taking it upon his ſalvation, much like <hi>Ireland, That he had never ſeen</hi> Garnett <hi>in ſixteen years;</hi> when it was afterwards diſcover'd, that he had been frequently in his company. But to ſhew ye, <hi>my Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> what a ſilly Calumny he infers, from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51086:26"/>Mr. <hi>Preſton</hi>'s being married, you are to obſerve that Marriage has been practis'd by their very Popes. <hi>Some of our Popes have been married,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aeneas Sylvius de Geſtis Concil. Baſil.</hi> And <hi>Aquinas</hi> allows the Marriage of Prieſts in theſe words: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus Conjugalis interdicitur Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotibus tantum jure humano, &amp; proinde diſpenſabile eſt.</hi> And <hi>Cajetanus</hi> avers the ſame: <hi>Non jure divino, ſed humano duntaxat prohibitum eſſe Conjugium Sacerdotibus, &amp; proinde in hoc diſpenſari poſſe.</hi> Marriage is not forbid to the Prieſts by divine, but only humane Law, and therefore is to be diſpenc'd with.</p>
            <p>Now why might not Mr. <hi>Preſton</hi> marry, the better to conceal himſelf, and yet be Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> but preſently Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> muſt be perjur'd for ſwearing it? Are theſe the great <hi>Perjuries</hi> the <hi>Obſervator</hi> has hunted out? Courage Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>—I dare be bold to ſecure ye thus far—Well— What now?—He was the Son of a <hi>Weaver,</hi> and therefore not fit compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for <hi>Jeſuites</hi>—Very good—What if he had been the <hi>Son of a Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi> What then? <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> was a Boy that kept <hi>Hogs</hi>—And what then? But the world knows better.</p>
            <p>Theſe are precious Arguments, <hi>my Beloved,</hi> to prove that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> knew nothing of the <hi>Plot.</hi> If he were ſo mean a perſon, they fitted his Capacity to a hair, for they ſent him up and down from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba</hi> with Letters. But if he had the wit to open theſe Letters, certainly he could not be ſo dull as not to underſtand the Contents. It will be their beſt way next time to chuſe a perſon of more wit, and leſs diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Oh—but he does not underſtand <hi>Latin</hi>—that's no <hi>Epitome,</hi> but an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth at large.—But ſuppoſe he did not; a Man muſt not be perjur'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he does not underſtand <hi>Latin</hi>—He underſtood <hi>Engliſh</hi> enough to bring them to their cold Beds.—</p>
            <p>But he never was at <hi>Salamanca,</hi> and conſequently never did his Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes.—That's but the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s ſaying—in oppoſition to which, Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> avers that he was at <hi>Salamanca,</hi> and that he did do his Exerciſes— <hi>Ergo Bellarmine.</hi>—</p>
            <p>He offers, that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> may ſend one, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> another, to know the truth of it.—Let him ce'n go himſelf and ſave charges. Upon theſe <hi>Goodly-good morrows</hi> he frames a hundred <hi>Riddle-me-Riddles, Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Surmiſes,</hi> and demands preſent Anſwer to a long Bed-roll of Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, with ſo much confidence, as if he were <hi>Pedagogue-Poſer-General</hi> of the Nation, and that all the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of the Land were his <hi>School boys,</hi> and bound to anſwer him.</p>
            <p>He would fain know what probability there was, <hi>That men of ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite Parts as they, ſhould trust ſuch a poor, abject, contemptible perſon as Mr.</hi> Oates, <hi>a perſon whom they had expell'd their Colledge for his ill Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, with a deſign of ſuch a high Concernment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, there was no Improbability at all. For alas, they were no ſuch high-flown, high-ſoaring wits, as he dreams 'em to be; but they were a company of pitiful, ſhabby, illiterate Dunces, that had not ſo much Scholarſhip as their Founder <hi>Loyala,</hi> and he as meer a <hi>Clodpate</hi> as ever por'd in Grammar. All which was evident from their Behavior at the Bar, and their filly Comments upon their own Letters. Neither had their Declamations any thing of the truth of Eloquence in 'em, but ſavor'd only of Themes, and Boys Exerciſes, which has been in part already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:51086:27"/>Then to his being Expell'd for his ill <hi>Qualities,</hi> there they betray'd their Folly moſt ſhamefully. For when it was expedient he ſhould be Expell'd, then he was Expell'd; when it was convenient he ſhould be at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> then he was at St. <hi>Omers, becauſe</hi> he could not <hi>come away:</hi> Nay, they brought ſixteen Witneſſes to prove that he kept cloſe at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and never ſtir'd out for ſo many moneths; and all this, after his Expulſion; which ſhew'd them to be meer Whifflers, and no true Maſters of Defence. So that this is the ſcope of the Author's deſign, to prove Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd, becauſe they could not prove themſelves innocent.</p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>Probitie</hi> of the Men (for he makes a ſad complaint, <hi>That</hi> 13 <hi>Chriſtian Men of great Probitie, ſhould have ſuch hard uſage</hi>) let us take a Catalogue of 'em.</p>
            <p>Hill, Green, <hi>and</hi> Berry, <hi>an Ale-houſe-keeper, a Cuſhion-man of a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and a Serving man, whoſe Converſation was not worth taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pickering, <hi>a pitiful, ignorant, lying Priest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ireland, <hi>a Smell-ſmock, that lay with his own Siſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gawen, <hi>call'd in queſtion at St.</hi> Omers <hi>it ſelf, and that was a wonder, for Buggery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fenwick, <hi>a Parſons Son, diſown'd by his Father, and by him Expell'd, for his Debauchery, from his Houſe, and in a fair way to be Hang'd, till he took Sanctuary at St.</hi> Omers, <hi>as Bankrupts do at</hi> Jamaica.</p>
            <p>Whitebread, <hi>the Provinicial; a Fiſher in all Profeſſions for Preferment. First a Jew, then a Presbyterian, then a Quaker, to whoſe Meetings he us'd to go in a Carters habit; one that had more ſhapes to diſguiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, then a Player, as is atteſted by a Letter written to the Lord Mayor of</hi> London: <hi>And at laſt a Jew again, that is, a wandering Jeſuite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Turner, <hi>a ſilly ignorant Fellow, that pray'd Nonſenſe at the Gallows, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring God to forgive him, and he would never offend him again, when he was next minute to be Hang'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Grove, <hi>a Raſcal not worth naming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Coleman, <hi>a conceited ambitious Fopp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Staley, <hi>a proud debauch'd Goldſmith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Langhorne, <hi>a Prieſt-ridden Bigott, but the beſt of 'em all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ay marry Sir, theſe are perſons qualifi'd indeed for a <hi>Plot.</hi> I confeſs, I ſhould have wonder'd that Men of <hi>Probitie</hi> ſhould have intrigu'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſuch a bloody deſign. But why ſuch Chriſtians, and <hi>Men of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitie</hi> as theſe, paſſing Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> neither in Birth, Learning, Parts or Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, (for they lay no other Crimes to his charge, but only <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Perjury,</hi> very ſlovenly urg'd upon him) ſhould be ſo abſtentions, as not to truſt Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> a ſtirring, active man, and a new Convert, the <hi>Abbrevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> muſt give a better Account then he does. But his and their Innocence may perhaps hang together in time, for Fame reports him at this time In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted of <hi>High-Treaſon;</hi> ſo that it is not his <hi>Innocence</hi> that makes him <hi>reſolute</hi> and <hi>conſtant,</hi> as he tells <hi>my Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> but a kind of <hi>Newgate</hi>-ſturdineſs, that makes him bold and confident.</p>
            <p>But now let me ask all Rational Men one Queſtion, <hi>What ſhould move Mr.</hi> Oates, <hi>to embrue his hands, ſo heatheniſhly, ſo barbarouſly, without any compaſſion, without any remorſe of conſcience, in ſo many ſtreams of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blod, without any cauſe, without any offence given him, but the petty Expulſion from a Colledge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:51086:27"/>The <hi>Compendium-Framer</hi> will ſay, <hi>The Hopes of Gain and Preferment.</hi> That's ſomething indeed. But how could Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> hope either for Gain or Preferment, by plunging himſelf into the diſcovery of a <hi>Chimera,</hi> from whence he could expect nothing but Ruine and Miſery in this world? For I omit the puniſhments of the other world, which it may be well an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, <hi>The wicked do not value,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How poorly does this <hi>Compendium Mechanic</hi> think of the King, the Council, and the Parliament, that they ſhould be ſo deluded and cajoll'd by the <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>contemptible</hi> parts of ſuch a pitiful Wretch as Mr. <hi>Oates?</hi> Is it to be imagin'd that ſo much <hi>Mercy,</hi> ſo much <hi>Piety,</hi> ſo much <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> ſhould proſtitute the Lives of ſo many Innocent perſons, to the ambitious Perjuries of Mr. <hi>Oates?</hi> Would the King have permitted ſuch a daring <hi>Titan,</hi> to ſcale the Heaven of Majeſty it ſelf, and not have immediately thunder'd him down into the loweſt Abyſs of his Disfavor? 'Tis not for a Worm of a Subject to the counterfeit image of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to tell the King of <hi>England,</hi> who is the real Vicegerent of God, what Perjury is; nor to flouriſh his pitiful Flag of Defiance againſt the <hi>Royal Standard</hi> of His determin'd <hi>Juſtice.</hi> When the King of <hi>England</hi> deſires to know what Perjury is, perhaps he may be perſuaded to addreſs Himſelf to this <hi>Muſhrome</hi> of a <hi>Compendium-Framer.</hi> In the mean time his <hi>Diminutive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> would do well to find out ſome other Employment, than to contend with his Sovereign, by rebelliouſly appealing from Him to His Subjects.</p>
            <p>As for his repeated Juſtification of the Murderers of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> I let it paſs, in regard it is but meerly Repetition, and there has been ſufficient Anſwer given already to all his Flaſhes and Evaſions. Only take notice by the way, how infamouſly induſtrious this <hi>Compendium-Scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> has been to aſſail no leſs then twice, in one <hi>Libel,</hi> the Publick Juſtice done upon thoſe more then <hi>prodigious Aſſaſſinates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>Diſpenſations,</hi> he talks as if he had a diſpenſation for what he wrote. For ſuch an Affront was never offer'd to the Popes Authority, at once to deprive him of the chiefeſt Howers of his Papal Prerogative, and ſo ample a part of his Revenue. But he ſays Lying is a <hi>ſottiſh</hi> and <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> Crime—ſo is <hi>Inceſt</hi>—But the Pope frequently diſpenſes with the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sin, why may he not as well diſpenſe with the former? Certainly if the Author of the <hi>Compendium</hi> had not had a plenary diſpenſation for Lying, he would never have told ſo many Untruths as he has done. Oh! but it is a great Evidence, that there are no diſpenſations for Lying, becauſe ſo many loſt Preferments and Employments for not taking the <hi>Teſt.</hi> A very ſilly Argument. For it would be a very <hi>ſottiſh</hi> and <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> thing indeed to lye and equivocate, where there was no occaſion; where there was no hazard of Life, no danger of endamaging the Cauſe <hi>of Popery;</hi> no Fear of bringing an irreparable Scandal <hi>upon the Profeſſion of the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion,</hi> there Conſtancy to their Mother the Church, carry'd a kind of Face of virtuous Piety and Chriſtian Patience; but when the Honour of the Pope, the Reputation of the Church, the Dignity of the Catholick Religion, lay all at ſtake, upon the ſingle Confeſſion of a barbarous Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a deteſtable Plot, there the Caſe is alter'd, there muſt be grains of allowance; upon ſuch an Occaſion Lying is no Lying, but a Pious and <hi>Sem-like</hi> covering the ſhame of our Father the Pope, and our Mother the Church, and their Daughter the <hi>Romiſh Religion.</hi> 'Tis true, ſome that needed neither Employment nor Preferment, refus'd the <hi>Teſt;</hi> but with others, and thoſe the far greater number, it went down as pleaſantly as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51086:28"/>Cream of Almonds. For which if they had no Diſpenſation, they cheated the Pope, and were Perſons of no Religion. But why do I inſiſt upon a Point, that he who diſputes againſt, diſputes againſt matter of Fact, and the practice of Popery for many and many Ages.</p>
            <p>As for that Renowned Prelate my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> I ſhall not preſume to intrude upon his concerns, unwilling to incur the Cenſure of the World, as if able to add the Leaſt mite to the perfections of his moſt accompliſht Learning.</p>
            <p>And thus (my Lords and Gentlemen,) you ſee how laborious, and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous this <hi>William with a wiſp</hi> has been, to lead your judgments aſtray, and ſeduce the Belief of the people. Now then moſt certain it is, that there was, if not ſtill on foot, a moſt hainons and deteſtable blot againſt the Life of our moſt Gracious Soveraign, the Government and Eſtabliſh'd Religion of the Nation. That this Plot was carried on by the Papiſts, is as certain; let them endeavour to ſhift it of how they can; which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by <hi>Coleman's</hi> own Letters, wherein we find no Correſpondence with Independants, or Presbyterians, or Quakers, but with Monſieur <hi>Ferryer,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> with <hi>Salamanca,</hi> and St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and with the <hi>Jeſuites, Benedictines,</hi> and ſeveral other Papiſts in <hi>England.</hi> He does not crave aid and aſſiſtance of money and men from the different Opinions of the Proteſtant Religion; but from the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> from the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> and the Contributions of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Roman Catholicks. Neither was his deſign againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> or <hi>Monarchy,</hi> but to ſubvert that <hi>Peſtilent Hereſie that had ſo long raigned in the Northern parts of the World;</hi> that is to ſay, all diſſenters in general from the Catholick Religion: by which, I ſay, 'tis evident, that the Papiſts were the Parties only concern'd. As certain it is, that upon the diſcovery of Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> this Plot was firſt examin'd and div'd into; and that ſoon after <hi>Sir Edmund bury Godfrey</hi> was baſely and treacherouſly murthered. As certain it is, that ſo ſoon as Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> had broke the Ice, ſeveral others came in, and confirm'd his evidence, perſons that he had never ſeen or Converſed with before. And to be ſhort, as certain it is, that upon their Evidence, after the mature examinations of King, Council and Parliament, ſeveral of theſe Popiſh Traitors have been convicted and executed.</p>
            <p>Now after all this, comes this Glowworm, with his nocturnal reflections in the tale of a <hi>Compendium,</hi> and to defend the Murtherers, he cries, <hi>How can this be, and how can that be?</hi> And againſt Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> he tears his throat, and baules out <hi>Perjury, Perjury,</hi> as if he were practiſing to cry Turneps and Carrots in a Winter morning.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>my Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> I will put the whole only upon this ſingle Iſſue whether you do believe that our Soveraign, (who if ever he did himſelf Injurie, it was always with a regard to the right hand of mercy, never to the left hand of Rigour,) can be ever thought to be much a deviatour from his own innate principles, as to harbour and protect in his own Royal Palace a perjur'd perſon; whoſe perjuries, if they may be ſo called, have not ſpar'd thoſe Grandeurs, which perhaps both you and I thought unapproachable.</p>
            <p>Upon this ſingle Iſſue, as I ſaid before, and upon this ſingle Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (ruminate while you pleaſe) I lay the ſtreſs of all that I have now to ſay, which is only this in few words.</p>
            <p>That ſince you have not the leaſt colour of reaſon in the world to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or miſdoubt the truth of this Plot, and murther ſo impudently endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51086:28"/>to be render'd <hi>fabulous</hi> end <hi>Chimerical</hi> by this Traitor of a Scribler. That you will conſider the inveterate and irreconcileable Antipathy of the Papiſts to the prevailing Grandeur of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>That you will conſider how much it concerns 'em at this time to lay about 'em with all the Thunder and Lightning imaginable, to diſpel, if they can, that diſmal cloud of Murder and Treaſon that threatens the very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Papacy, already the ſcandal of Chriſtianity, and the contempt of Turciſm.</p>
            <p>That you would conſider how it has been the continual practice of their Church, by the indirect means of Lying and Scandal, to conceal their perpetrated Villanies, or fix 'em upon the Innocent; and that it has been their continual Cuſtom and Maxim, to endeavor the propagation of their Faith, by Deſtruction and Maſſacre: which both <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> with Tears can teſtifie, and the Ruinous War of <hi>Germany</hi> by them fomented and carried on; as if there were no way to recover their decaying Hereſie, but by laying Blood to the root of it.</p>
            <p>Then upon theſe Conſiderations make this farther Progreſs: Let 'em not think their Liberties ſo involv'd in yours. That they cannot fall, but you muſt precipitate: Let 'em not think to amuſe ye, that Proteſtants cannot be ſafe, becauſe the Papiſts are deſervedly proſecuted for their Crimes. They had Priviledges ſufficient, Immunities enough, all Indulgence imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: but they have forfeited all by Conſpiracy, and Murther of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that <hi>Fountain</hi> from whence all their mercy flow'd. They would have depriv'd you of your Lives and Liberties, your Wives, Children, and Eſtates; and now they cry, <hi>The Proteſtants cannot be ſafe,</hi> becauſe ſome few of the Traytors have been meritoriouſly Hang'd, and more like to be. They plot and contrive, and being detected, cry out, <hi>Perjury, the Land groans under the Sin of Perjury.</hi> But let 'em know they are not done with yet; and let this Traytor of an <hi>Epitomizer</hi> be aſſur'd, there is that Evidence in Bank, that will in time ſtill the noiſe of his nefarious yawling.</p>
            <p>Since then, <hi>my Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> the Providence of Heaven has been ſo miraculoufly pleas'd to diſcover theſe dark Intrigues of Popery, that would have been the utter ruine of King and Countrey, of Religion, Life and Fortune, Uphold and Maintain that Teſtimony to which you owe your Preſervation: and let it not ſuffer under the Scandal and Reproach of thoſe that ſuffer juſtly by it. For the ſake of all that is good and holy, proſecute the preſent Diſcovery; which being born up by an untainted and daily increaſing Evidence, has not only deſtroy'd the hopes of our Enemies, but ſhaken the very Baſis and Foundation of the Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now the God of Peace preſerve the King of</hi> Salem, <hi>from whom, as He hath been hitherto indefatigably watchful for our Tranquility, we have no reaſon but ſtill to hope the future enjoyment of Proſperity and Plenty, of our Laws, Religion and Liberties, ſo long as ſo Good and Gracious a Sovereign remains well guarded againſt the Treaſons of Popery, by the Obedience and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity of his Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
